<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Plutosoft delimited</title><link href="http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/</id><updated>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>on batch processing audio speech to text.</title><link href="http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/on-batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2017-04-22:/speech-to-text/on-batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Recognize speech, not wreck a nice beach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People nowadays commonly use speech-to-text tools for myriad uses,
including writing text messages, entering todo lists,
and writing emails.  However, increasing numbers of enterprising
sorts including just plain folk are starting to warm up to
using dictation software for writing longer form content …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Recognize speech, not wreck a nice beach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People nowadays commonly use speech-to-text tools for myriad uses,
including writing text messages, entering todo lists,
and writing emails.  However, increasing numbers of enterprising
sorts including just plain folk are starting to warm up to
using dictation software for writing longer form content
such as journals and even novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dictation software has been generally available for many years,
in the form of
commercial off the shelf application software, text editors in desktop
operating systems, notepads in tablet devices,
email clients in mobile phones,
and more recently in cloud-based document editors, available
to the user from any device that can run a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if you have a large-ish number of audio files?
It turns out there isn't an easy way to handle even modestly sized
batches of files using those just aforementioned tools.
There do exist commercially available alternatives, which will gladly
take those batches of audio files off your hands and return
high quality text. But these are still rather
human labor intensive, which means that they remain
unaffordable to the typical consumer who is a tad long-winded,
much less the odd sort who just happens to have a boat load of such files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, an affordable alternative is emerging, if
you're willing to write a bit of code.
The hyperscale cloud api providers are making their deep
learning models available for a small fraction of the dollar cost and
effortlessly handling large batches in a single bound.
Although there is still that small issue of having to write some code
in order to get this amazing cost and time reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although generally available,
there is a still a ways to go before these APIs are generally useful
for converting conversational audio recorded in the wild using
mobile phones amidst noisy ambient sounds.
Nonetheless, the results are good enough
and the pricing low enough that the time has come to dip
my metaphorical toes in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to write more about my experiences using these
powerful cloud APIs, so stay tuned for more if this is of interest
to you.  Although I myself tend to cringe when the blogger ends
their post by promising an enticing followup, which invariably never
comes.  But I really do sincerely intend to write more on this.
Of course, that's what they all would say, I'm sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already compiled a backlog of interesting results just waiting
to be converted into
intriguing visuals and wrapped in witty yet insightful prose. Promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the interim,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Background"&gt;here is some additional background on the project and results of a preliminary comparison between IBM and Google&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing, my findings indicate to me that I should be able to
extract useful text from my recordings.  These cloud APIs cannot be
trained on my voice, and so as yet do not have the same quality as
do personalized devices.
The text they generate is largely recognizable to me, although
that is often in the same way as my handwriting is recognizable to me
because I vaguely remember generating it.
The error rates are still too high
for these transcripts to allow me to reliably parse meaningful
whole sentences much less serve as document of record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I think they may be suitable for indexing the audio files
to make them more amenable to search. I do expect that they
will be adequately informative to support meaningful textmining and trend
analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting just how easy it is for a badly transcribed
sequence of just a few words in a row to turn an entire sentence
into complete gibberish. We humans are pretty amazing in how well
we can actually understanding each other's speech despite the noise
cocktail party din much less the hearing loss and tinnitus and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, be that as it may, I am hopeful.  I see a future where
it will be possible to attain human level accuracy even from the low bit rate
and high noise level recordings that are to be had from our mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.
.
.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h6&gt;fin&lt;/h6&gt;</content></entry></feed>