<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Plutoware delimited - misc</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/</id><updated>2018-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>How to showcase your Apache Spark skills</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/how-to-showcase-your-apache-spark-skills.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2018-07-29:/speech-to-text/how-to-showcase-your-apache-spark-skills.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How to spotlight your Apache Spark skills&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align="right" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/L4.UI.DAG.png" alt="Spark UI DAG" width="230px"
/&gt;
How do you prove your capability as a Apache Spark data scientist when you don’t have much to show? Perhaps this is because you don’t have much experience. Perhaps it is because the work you do cannot be shown. 
You may …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How to spotlight your Apache Spark skills&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align="right" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/L4.UI.DAG.png" alt="Spark UI DAG" width="230px"
/&gt;
How do you prove your capability as a Apache Spark data scientist when you don’t have much to show? Perhaps this is because you don’t have much experience. Perhaps it is because the work you do cannot be shown. 
You may have done impressive work, but have nothing to share because most developers work for companies that don’t publish their code as open source. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my long career 
as data scientist and machine learning developer, I have learned many useful lessons for organizing information and presenting it effectively. 
I have created online courses to help the aspiring &lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/spark-sql"&gt;data scientist&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/sparkml-features"&gt;machine learning developer&lt;/a&gt;. 
This article is going to delve more into how to present yourself. 
I am going to give you some tips for bringing your skills out of the dark and into the light. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Publish your work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publishing a code project is a great way to introduce yourself to an interviewer. This also provides the interviewer 
with ample talking points for various styles of interview questions. Doing this makes the interviewers job easier. 
You are giving them context on what you already know. 
You also provide them with talking points for initiating discussion. 
Interviewers in the software industry are often stretched thin. 
Making their job easier puts them into a better mood. 
This also demonstrates your preparedness. This type of preparation can be helpful for many types of interview questions, including behavioral questions, situational questions, coding challenges, and system design challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Show what you know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I will show you how you can showcase your Apache Spark skills. I’ll show you how publishing your work in a self-contained manner using informative visualizations can separate your from the pack.  I’ll also show how to select a coding project that demonstrates useful skills that are immediately applicable in a production setting.  Furthermore, in setting this up you acquire skills that are valuable for the coding challenge portion of the interview. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Know what you show&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To utilize this approach effectively, you must be intimately familiar with every line of content in your repo. The best way to achieve this is to create an original work of your own design, developed from start to finish by yourself. Once you get started this may not take as long as you expect. On the other hand, there may be steps that blossom into much more time-intensive investment than you expected.  That's actually ok -- it gives you something interesting to explain when discussing your process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hone your edge, gain a new one&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone who has well organized and nontrivial open source code will be prioritised over other similarly experienced candidates because their competencies are easier to evaluate.  By providing visibility you simplify the job of the recruiters and interviewers, while simultaneously preparing yourself for the interview. Even better, you may learn skills that will be useful on the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we will cover&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first part of this article, I'll show an example code repository.
In the second part I'll discuss strategy for selecting a code project. 
In the third part I'll give some ideas for a coding project suitable for 
Apache Spark. 
In the fourth part I'll show how you can supplement this approach with 
visualizations obtained from Apache Spark log output and the Spark UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Example repo&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, take 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp"&gt;this python repo&lt;/a&gt; that I published on github. 
I developed this during my role as a mentor for a robotics team to teach students how to use a code repository.
The repo uses &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/blob/master/README.md"&gt;the readme&lt;/a&gt; to explain the project at a high level manner while also 
giving a developer a quick start guide. 
Often overlooked, &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/wiki"&gt;the repo wiki&lt;/a&gt;
is a great way to elaborate further in breadth as well as depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wiki is a great place to provide visuals that allow readers to quickly get a sense of what your project does. 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/raw/master/images/stage3_paths_ne.png"&gt;Figure 1&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/raw/master/images/stage2_fleur_de_lis.png"&gt;Figure 2&lt;/a&gt; 
are two of the more visually appealing visualizations from this project. 
They give the reader an idea at a glance of what is being done and how, and draw the reader in to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/raw/master/images/stage2_fleur_de_lis.png" alt="Fleur-de-lis search pattern (copyright Mark E Plutowski)" width="400px"/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 1. Fleur-de-lis search pattern &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1 shows a fleur-de-lis search pattern used by an algorithm that I developed for a simple offline geometric planner. Not only is it an appealing visualization, it also illustrates a key step in the algorithm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/raw/master/images/stage3_paths_ne.png" alt="Sample trajectories (copyright Mark E Plutowski)" width="400px"/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 2 sample trajectories found by the planner&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows trajectories discovered by the planner for one of the goal states overlaid on a depiction of the playing field. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Displaying depth and breadth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas space in a resume is limited, the wikified repo format 
provides ample space to emphasize your abilities to arbitrary breadth and depth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/blob/master/README.md"&gt;readme page&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/wiki"&gt;the wiki home page&lt;/a&gt; to link to other pages that provide context for what you were trying to accomplish, and why your approach is sensible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/wiki/Background"&gt;Background&lt;/a&gt; page of my repo gives a brief primer on Alternative Approaches, and Implementation Steps. The next sections explain the why, what, and how of the project. You could use something similar to demonstrate your depth of understanding of specific techniques. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/wiki/RelatedApproaches"&gt;Related Approaches page&lt;/a&gt; 
of the repo gives a brief primer on specific alternative approaches that were considered, which one was selected, and why. You could use this to demonstrate your breadth of understanding of a field of interest.  The &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/wiki/Planning-Stages"&gt;Planning Stages page&lt;/a&gt; describes what the code actually does.  It gives links to python notebooks containing visualizations, such as &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/blob/master/sample_trajectories.ipynb"&gt;this sample trajectories notebook&lt;/a&gt;. This allows an interviewer to review your code and see how it behaves on actual data, because when you check in the notebook, you also check in the results from the latest run. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notebooks allow you to blend code and visuals and tell the story behind your code without cluttering up the code itself. This &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/first2017mp/blob/master/test.ipynb"&gt;test page&lt;/a&gt; from my repo gives data from tests designed to simulate the code under realistic conditions and demonstrate its use of compute resources. This type of presentation demonstrates a data-driven mindset and indicates that you know how to test your code rigorously. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Customize to your needs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably wouldn’t need all of these pages. I did them all because it was instructive for the robot team participants. My comprehensive approach serves to illustrate the various types of information that may can be shown.  You must decide for yourself which ones are relevant for showcasing your competencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most readers may not delve deep, but for those that do are able to glean more information about your qualifications. You can also refer back to this during the interview. On the other hand, if your intended role values brevity more than comprehensive coverage and succinctness is an important element of style, then you should go for that instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these assets an interviewer could explore multiple aspects of your skill as a developer, such as your ability to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decompose a complex problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design a multifacted system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up a new code repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organize a code repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write performant code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visualize key results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicate effectively &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already stated but which bears repeating, this eases the burden on the interviewer.  Providing these assets gives the interviewer opportunity to derive behavioral questions. It conversely gives you ample content you can use to answer those behavioral questions. Use the STAR technique, by describing the situation (&lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;), distilling it down to a single task (&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;), and the key action (&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;) you used to solve it, concluding with the result (&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also provides code screeners with code examples they can use as a starting point for more in depth exploration of your skills. Instead of selecting a random problem for the coding challenge, they may choose one that is within your wheelhouse. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Showcasing your repo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review code repositories relevant to your own goals and learn how to distinguish effective ones from half-baked ones. Pick one or two to serve as a role model for your own design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Choosing a coding project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many new developers make the mistake of picking code projects similar to what they encountered in an academic setting. These are often not relevant to a real-world job as a commercial software developer, because they exclude some of the messier aspects of a commercial application, such as cleansing a dataset, putting data into a form that can be utilized by an efficient algorithm, testing edge cases, and analyzing complex results. Interviewers want to see that you possess knowledge and can learn quickly, but even better if you are familiar with heterogeneous aspects of a development task. A well known AI researcher once said that in the university setting they spent 20% of their time prepping the dataset and 80% on the algorithm development, whereas in a commercial setting this ratio was reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choose well&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your mission is to showcase your ability to apply Apache Spark to a nontrivial real dataset. As a general rule of thumb -- if you didn’t need to perform any data cleansing or preprocessing on the dataset, the data wasn’t messy enough to be realistic.  If your solution ran in a few seconds it was not challenging enough to test your algorithms. If it didn’t exhaust at least half of the memory available to your system and run the fan to cool the cpu, then you probably could increase the complexity of the task, either by tackling a larger dataset, or by subjecting the dataset to on a more challenging analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I find that the best portfolio projects are less about doing fancy 
   modeling and more about working with interesting data." - &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jasonkgoodman/
   advice-on-building-data-portfolio-projects-c5f96d8a0627"&gt;Advice on 
   Building Data Portfolio Projects&lt;/a&gt;, J.Goodman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to choosing a code project to show in your portfolio is authenticity. 
If this is not a true representation of what you can do, it can backfire. 
You want the reader to know that this is an original creation of your own making. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ideas for a coding project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Migrate an existing solution to Spark&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, there might already be an existing solution for solving a problem.  Your mission is to migrate the solution to Apache Spark and compare the results. Many such datasets and associated solutions that you can use as a point of departure exist online. I performed a &lt;a href="http://qr.ae/TUIbIH"&gt;similar exercise myself (2016)&lt;/a&gt;, migrating a proof-of-concept classification application from scikit/numpy to PySpark, converting it into a stacked ensemble, and tuning it to be able to handle sixty thousand input features and five hundred thousand training data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple years later, Databricks published the results of comparing PySpark and Pandas: &lt;a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2018/05/03/benchmarking-apache-spark-on-a-single-node-machine.html"&gt;Benchmarking Apache Spark on a Single Node Machine&lt;/a&gt;. 
demonstrating that Spark can even be faster than single-node PyData tools because Spark can more easily utilize all cores due to its built-in parallelism. 
This study found Spark can also have lower memory consumption because it does not require loading the entire data set into memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use Spark to analyze a nontrivial data set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By nontrivial I mean something that takes more than a few seconds to process.  Using a challenging dataset can help make your project more credible. It makes the results more interesting, and gives you more to talk about.  The &lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/spark-sql"&gt;Learning Apache Spark SQL&lt;/a&gt; course uses a 6.5 MiB dataset containing 1,095,695 words, 128,467 lines, and 41,762 distinct words. This size of dataset is just large enough to pose a challenge to a standard development grade laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img id="img1" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/frequent_5-tuples.png" alt="Frequent 5 tuples" width="600px"
/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 4. Most frequent 5 tuples in The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 4 shows the most frequent 5-tuples extracted from "The Project Gutenberg EBook of The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle", obtained using &lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/spark-sql"&gt;Spark SQL&lt;/a&gt; via a moving window function query.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Compare Apache Spark using two different programming languages.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As PySpark's compilers continue to improve, the &lt;a href="https://github.com/archivesunleashed/aut/files/1997998/udf_performance_doc.pdf"&gt;difference between using python and scala continues to narrow&lt;/a&gt;. If you do everything using Spark SQL, then from there the &lt;a href="https://mindfulmachines.io/blog/2018/6/apache-spark-scala-vs-java-v-python-vs-r-vs-sql26"&gt;performance is equivalent&lt;/a&gt;. 
This comparison attracts keen interest as developers naturally 
attempt to reconcile the tension between ease of use and optimal performance.
Just be sure that your &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/32464122/spark-performance-for-scala-vs-python"&gt;implementation in each language is efficient&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Compare Spark to an alternative parallel computing platform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this approach, you select a data set, and perform an analysis of it using two different cluster computing paradigms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a popular analysis because developers are always interested in comparing the performance of competing tools.  However, you better know each tool very well if you choose to explain this analysis in an interview setting 
because you need to understand each platform equally well. Here are some other ideas you can use to come up with your own comparative analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apache Spark vs Flink&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spark vs Hive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spark vs Map-Reduce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spark vs Storm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python Numpy or Pandas vs Spark on a single node.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python multiprocessing run on high-memory multi-cpu instance vs Spark on a cluster of commodity instances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use Spark in conjunction with a cloud api&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud apis provide powerful means of handling large datasets for certain applications; however, preparing the data for the cloud api may require substantial preprocessing. Cloud apis can also generate a lot of log data.  For example, I compared &lt;a href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/on-batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html"&gt;IBM Watson and the Google Cloud speech-to-text cloud apis&lt;/a&gt;, 
and then compared the results by using sql to analyze the log data (cf., 
&lt;a href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/on-bleu-scores-and-transcription-rates.html"&gt;on bleu scores and transcription rates&lt;/a&gt;, 
and &lt;a href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/on-transcription-rate-for-noisy-recordings-ibm-ftw.html"&gt;on transcription rate for noisy recordings&lt;/a&gt;.  In this case, I used sqlite to run the queries. 
When I redo this I plan to use Spark SQL instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of project gives you even more to talk about: how to integrate Spark with a cloud api, what operations are suitable for Spark and which ones are more suitable to do within the cloud api, what post-processing analytics steps are there for which Spark is especially suitable.  This demonstrates that you are not just expecting to run Spark in a sandbox isolated from other systems; you have some knowledge of how to use Spark to leverage other powerful computing frameworks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img hspace=10x src="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/blob/master/images/bleu_score_deciles.png?raw=true" alt="Bleu scores, IBM vs Google" width="600px"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Use Spark to extract training features from a data set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many data science jobs require the ability to train statistical models based on feature data gleaned from raw data. There is an abundance of data that you could use to demonstrate your ability to perform this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/spark-sql"&gt;Apache Spark SQL course&lt;/a&gt; 
shows how to extract moving-window n-tuples from a text corpus. This would provide a good starting point for a feature extractor that vectorizes this into a form that can be provided as input to a neural network model. 
My &lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/sparkml-features"&gt;Apache Spark ML course&lt;/a&gt; shows how to convert these n-tuples from arrays of strings to the sparse integer arrays used by Spark.ML's machine learning models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img id="img1" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/moving_4tuples.png" alt="moving 4-tuples" width="550px"
/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 5. moving 4-tuples &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 5 shows moving 4-tuples extracted from the text corpus "The Project Gutenberg EBook of The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle". Each row corresponds to a shifting ahead of the window one word 
relative to the previous row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of modeling tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistically improbable phrases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anomaly detection &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic modeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trend analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of relevant models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approximate K Nearest Neighbors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternating Least Squares&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;K-means clustering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streaming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can generate features for one of these types of models or tasks start-to-finish end-to-end, you are probably able to handle other modeling tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Demonstrating your knowledge of Spark internals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to program the Spark computing framework is good.&lt;br&gt;
Being able to sensibly explain how it actually executed your code 
is better.  Being able to discuss how you would restructure the code 
or tune key parameters to improve the use of a critical compute resource 
is even better. Spark provides several means of generating visualizations 
that you can use to illustrate the compute resources used by 
your Spark code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to use the Spark UI to analyze performance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've developed your Spark application and run it on a realistic dataset,
you'll want to demonstrate it in action. 
Even better if you can display your understanding of compute resources 
used by Spark when executing your code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spark UI is extremely useful for evaluating its usage of computing resources such as cpu, memory, i/o, and data transfer. 
This figure shows the Spark UI details for a sql query, 
showing the number of rows of data scanned, the number of files loaded, 
how much memory was used, and whether any data was spilled to disk from cache. 
Being able to analyze the internals of a system is an extremely practical 
skill that is desirable for most development positions, including data scientists. Being able to explain what this graph means and how it relates to your code would be an excellent way to convey your understanding of how your
code is executed by the system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 6. Spark UI details for a sql query &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/L4.a.UI.SQL.query5.Plan1.png" alt="Spark UI DAG" width="800px"
/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 6 shows the resource consumption of a Spark query using the SQL tab within the Spark UI for a moving window query over 68 MiB of data, comprising 75,485 rows.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img id="img1" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/L4.a.UI.Sql.query5.Plan3.png" alt="Spark UI DAG" width="800px"
/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 7. Query plans &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 7 shows query plans used by the Spark query shown in Figure 6. 
This may suggest questions about the difference between different flavors of logical plan. It could be used to compare and contrast a logical plan and physical plan. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img id="img1" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/L4.UI.DAG2.png" alt="Spark UI DAG" width="400px"
/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 8. Detailed DAG Visualization &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 8 shows a DAG visualization similar to the DAG visualization in the 
very first figure shown at the top of this article, but with additional detail enabled. Don't display this level of detail if you cannot back it up with 
answers to the questions it may trigger; but if you can pull that off you 
will be a more credible candidate. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img id="img1" hspace=10x src="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/spark/L4.UI.TE1.png" alt="Spark UI DAG" width="800px"
/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Figure 9. Spark UI Executors tab &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 9 shows the Executors tab in the Spark UI for an application that 
had completed 40327 tasks over the course of 3.3 hours on a single node cluster having eight cores. This evokes several questions, such as what does the number of tasks correspond to?  How do you suppose the compute resource consumption might have changed if running on a cluster instead of on a single node? It appears that 282 GB of data were inputted, but the amount of shuffle write was small.  What might explain this? 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the competency required to win a desirable role is necessary but not sufficient. You also need to demonstrate your competency during the interview process.  This depends on communicating your understanding effectively. You can accomplish much of this in advance, by tackling a code project and publishing it. Writing up key results in a visually appealing way makes the 
presentation more compelling and puts your skills in a better light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To learn more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see additional tips and project ideas, see my insanely low-priced online courseware on 
&lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/spark-sql"&gt;Learning Apache Spark SQL&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href="https://learn-apache-spark.thinkific.com/courses/sparkml-features"&gt;Learning Apache Spark ML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Review of A Cooperative Species</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/review-of-a-cooperative-species.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2018-05-20:/speech-to-text/review-of-a-cooperative-species.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Contents&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a summarized version of the book 
&lt;strong&gt;A Cooperative Species : Human Reciprocity and Its Evolution&lt;/strong&gt; 
By Samuel Bowles &amp;amp; Herbert Gintis, 2011. &lt;a href="library.uniteddiversity.coop/Cooperatives/A_Cooperative_Species-Human_Reciprocity_and_Its_Evolution.pdf"&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Samuel Stebbins Bowles&lt;/em&gt; is an American economist and Professor Emeritus at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, where he continues to teach courses on microeconomics and the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Contents&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a summarized version of the book 
&lt;strong&gt;A Cooperative Species : Human Reciprocity and Its Evolution&lt;/strong&gt; 
By Samuel Bowles &amp;amp; Herbert Gintis, 2011. &lt;a href="library.uniteddiversity.coop/Cooperatives/A_Cooperative_Species-Human_Reciprocity_and_Its_Evolution.pdf"&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Samuel Stebbins Bowles&lt;/em&gt; is an American economist and Professor Emeritus at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, where he continues to teach courses on microeconomics and the theory of institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herbert Gintis&lt;/em&gt; continues to research econ &amp;amp; morality, and is also a frequent book reviewer on Amazon.com. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contains excerpts and paraphrased quotes from the book.  The book's authors claim that it is intended to be a scientific description of how human's behave in decision-making group settings, and not how they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; behave.  Likewise, if an excerpt is interpreted as a recommendation for how people &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; behave, such an impression not intended.  This summary is intended to distill the book down to the essence of the author's claims, only, and not to emphasize or de-emphasize any claims except where they might detract from brevity -- such as in-depth details of experimental studies and formal proofs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 275 page book is distilled to 34 pages of excerpts. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Document statistics for the original book :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;275 of pdf formatted text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;202 pages of raw text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;120,458 words  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;770,779 bytes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summarized version has 34 pages &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;34 pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;749   lines &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10,475  words (8.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;69,031 bytes (8.8%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Editor’s Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do humans, uniquely among animals, cooperate in large numbers to advance projects for the common good? Contrary to the conventional wisdom in biology and economics, this generous and civic-minded behavior is widespread and can not be explained simply by far-sighted self-interest or to desire to help close genealogical kin. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In A Cooperative Species, Samuel Bowles and Herbert Gintis - pioneers in the new experimental and evolutionary science of human behavior - show that the central issue is not why selfish people act genetically, but instead how genetic and cultural evolution has produced a species in which substantial numbers make sacrifices to uphold ethical norms and to help even total strangers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors describe how, for thousands of generations, cooperation with fellow group members has been essential to survival. Groups that created institutions to protect the civic-minded from exploitation by the selfish flourished and prevailed in conflicts with less cooperative groups. Key to this process was the evolution of social emotions such as shame and guilt, and our capacity to internalize social norms so that acting ethically became a personal goal rather than simply to prudent way to avoid punishment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using experimental, archaeological, genetic, and ethnographic data to calibrate models of the coevolution of genes and culture as well as prehistoric warfare and other forms of group competition, A Cooperative Species provides a compelling and novel account of how humans came to be moral and cooperative . Key to this process was the evolution of social emotions such as shame and guilt and our capacity to internalize social norms so that acting ethically became a personal goal rather than simply to prudent way to avoid punishment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summarized -- excerpts from the book&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 1 A Cooperative Species&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;reciprocal altruism (which really should be called “enlightened self-interest”) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[non-cooperative] models fail to explain two facts about human cooperation: that it takes place in groups far larger than the immediate family, and that both in real life and in laboratory experiments, it occurs in interactions that are unlikely to be repeated, and where it is impossible to obtain reputational gains from cooperating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we seek to explain why we are not purely selfish—why the social preferences that sustain altruistic cooperation are so common&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of our subsequent history we created novel social and physical environments exhibiting similar, or even greater, benefits of cooperation, among them the division of labor coordinated by market exchange and respect of rights of property, systems of production characterized by increasing returns to scale (irrigated agriculture, modern industry, information systems with network externalities), and warfare. The impressive scope of these modern forms of cooperation was facilitated by the emergence in the last seven millennia of governments capable of enforcing property rights and providing incentives for the self-interested to contribute to common projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;prior to the emergence of governments and since, cooperation has been sustained also by motives that led some people to bear costs on behalf of others, contributing to common projects, punishing transgressors, and excluding outsiders. In the pages that follow we will advance three reasons why these altruistic social preferences supporting cooperation outcompeted unmitigated and amoral self-interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, human groups have devised ways to protect their altruistic members from exploitation by the self-interested. Prominent among these is the public-spirited shunning, ostracism, and even execution of free-riders and others who violate cooperative norms. Other group activities protecting altruists from exploitation are leveling practices that limit hierarchy and inequality, including sharing food and information. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, humans adopted prolonged and elaborate systems of socialization that led individuals to internalize the norms that induce cooperation, so that contributing to common projects and punishing defectors became objectives in their own right rather than constraints on behavior. Together, the internalization of norms and the protection of the altruists from exploitation served to offset, at least partially, the competitive handicaps born by those who were motivated to bear personal costs to benefit others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, between-group competition for resources and survival was and remains a decisive force in human evolutionary dynamics. Groups with many cooperative members tended to survive these challenges and to encroach upon the territory of the less cooperative groups, thereby both gaining reproductive advantages and proliferating cooperative behaviors through cultural transmission. The extraordinarily high stakes of intergroup competition and the contribution of altruistic cooperators to success in these contests meant that sacrifice on behalf of others, extending beyond the immediate family and even to virtual strangers, could proliferate. Modern-day nationalism is an example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boundary-maintenance supported within-group cooperation and exchange by limiting group size and within-group linguistic, normative and other forms of heterogeneity. Insider favoritism also sustained the between-group conflicts and differences in behavior that made group competition a powerful evolutionary force&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;institutions proliferated because the groups that adopted them secured high levels of within-group cooperation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These capacities allow us to formulate general norms of social conduct, to erect social institutions regulating this conduct, to communicate these rules and what they entail in particular situations, to alert others to their violation and to organize coalitions to punish the violators. No less important is the psychological capacity to internalize norms, to experience such social emotions as shame and moral outrage, and to base group membership on such nonkin characteristics as ethnicity and language, which in turn facilitates costly conflicts among groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the individual motives and group-level institutions that account for cooperation among humans include not only the most elevated, including a concern for others, fair-mindedness, and democratic accountability of leaders, but also the most wicked, such as vengeance, racism, religious bigotry, and hostility toward outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Price-fixing by cartels and other baleful economic effects of collusion motivated Adam Smith to advocate a competitive economic system under which such forms of antisocial collusion would unravel. In its stead he advocated “an invisible hand” that would guide the efforts of countless self-interested producers to coordinate a modern division of labor in the interest of all, a stunning example of mutualistic cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if the late 18th century gave us this evocative metaphor for the beneficial effects of the pursuit of individual gain, the mid-20th century invented two no less riveting metaphors for the dark side of self-interest: the prisoner’s dilemma and the tragedy of the commons. Their logic inverted Adam Smith’s invisible hand, showing that even where cooperation was essential to the pursuit of common ends, it would falter in the face of self-interest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social preferences, Hardin made clear, were powerless to counter the “remorseless” degradation of the environment: … “freedom in a commons means ruin for all,” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mancur Olson’s no less ineluctable “logic of collective action” in n-person prisoner’s dilemmas demonstrated the inevitability of a passive citizenry and the impossibility of cooperation, due to ubiquitous free-riders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pyotr Kropotkin’s Mutual Aid a century earlier, a book that had advanced a kinder, gentler view of the evolutionary process in opposition to the then popular dog-eat-dog Social Darwinist claims about what natural selection entails for human behavior&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[We] show that evolution can not only foster self-interest but also promote the generous and ethical behaviors that help us escape the prisoner’s dilemma and avert the tragedy of the commons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[We show] that this is true not despite, but in important measure because, evolutionary processes are “red in tooth and claw,” in Alfred, Lord Tennyson’s famous words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 2. The Evolution of Altruism in Humans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans. . . are fond of explaining almost all the actions of their lives by the principle of self-interest -- Alexis de Tocqueville, Democracy in America, 1835&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;modern game theory [is a] folk theorem [intending to explain how] close family members, repeated interactions and reputation-building might confer fitness advantages and other benefits on those engaging in seemingly unselfish behaviors. [emphasis added]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach, however, favors Tocqueville, not Tocqueville’s Americans. Explaining why will take us through disciplines as diverse as population genetics, experimental economics, evolutionary game theory, and archaeology and across semantic minefields of heavily freighted terms, such as altruism, and controversial scientific questions, such as the relationship between genetic inheritance and cultural transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.1 Preferences, Beliefs, and Constraints&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explore the proximal influences on an individual action such as helping using the &lt;strong&gt;beliefs, preferences, and constraints&lt;/strong&gt; approach common to economics and decision theory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to this approach, what individuals do when restricted to a specific set of feasible actions depends on their &lt;strong&gt;desires&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;goals&lt;/strong&gt; on the one hand, and their &lt;strong&gt;beliefs&lt;/strong&gt; on the other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;constraints&lt;/strong&gt; represent the limitations placed on the feasible actions an individual may take in a given situation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beliefs&lt;/strong&gt; are an individual’s representation of the causal structure of the world, including the relationship between the individual’s actions and the probabilities of the various possible resulting outcomes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preferences&lt;/strong&gt; are the pro or con sentiments that make up the individual’s valuation of the various possible outcomes of taking an action. Preferences may be described as an ordering (technically, a preference function) of the states of the world that may result from one’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assume preferences satisfy two conditions: 
1. they are &lt;strong&gt;complete&lt;/strong&gt; (any two states can be compared) and 
2. transitive; that is, &lt;strong&gt;consistent&lt;/strong&gt;, so that if one prefers A to B and B to C, one then prefers A to C. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preferences are the results of a variety of influences: tastes (food likes and dislikes, for example), habits, emotions (such as shame or anger) and other visceral reactions (such as fear), the manner in which individuals construe situations (or more narrowly, the way they frame decisions), commitments (like promises), internalized norms of ethical behavior, psychological propensities (for aggression, extroversion and the like), and affective relationships with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can succinctly and analytically summarize the individual’s behavior as maximization of a preference function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say that individuals act on their preferences means that knowledge of these preferences provides a concise and accurate account of their actions, given their beliefs and constraints . &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A version of the beliefs, preferences, and constraints model, incorporating the behavioral assumptions sometimes summarized as Homo economicus, has become standard not only in economics but throughout the human behavioral sciences. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F. Y. Edgeworth, a founder of neoclassical economics, “&lt;em&gt;The first principle of economics is that every agent is actuated only by self interest&lt;/em&gt;” (1881). 
Edgeworth followed the statement above with the caveat that the axiom was strictly true only in “contract and war.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But self-interest need not be part of the preferences, beliefs, and constraints approach. Preferences could be altruistic or even masochistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the self-interest axiom&lt;/strong&gt;: people seek to maximize their expected payoffs and believe that others do the same&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economist’s usual defense of the self-interest axiom is that it is self-evident, with the fallback assertion being that natural selection could not have produced any other kind of preferences. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[They show that] the assertion is far from self-evident, and in fact is simply false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2 Social Preferences and Social Dilemmas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;social preferences&lt;/strong&gt; are a concern for the well-being of others and a desire to uphold ethical norms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;self-regarding preferences&lt;/strong&gt; … are based on states concerning oneself alone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;other-regarding&lt;/strong&gt; : as valuations based at least in part on states that occur to others&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An other-regarding player cares about not only his own payoff, but that of his partner as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethical commitments&lt;/strong&gt; may reflect a concern for the states experienced by others, but need not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One can be honest because one seeks to avoid imposing costs on others by deceiving them. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But honesty could be entirely self-regarding, practiced in order to be the kind of person one wants to be. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus the textbook “economic man” would be described not only as &lt;strong&gt;self-regarding&lt;/strong&gt;, but as &lt;strong&gt;amoral&lt;/strong&gt; as well, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we use the simpler description — &lt;strong&gt;self regarding&lt;/strong&gt; —when the meaning is clear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;self-esteem&lt;/strong&gt; is dependent in part upon what others think of us, so we attempt to favorably impress others as a means of raising our subjective self-esteem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We prefer the term “&lt;strong&gt;social preferences&lt;/strong&gt;” to the more common but ambiguous “unselfish” or “non-self-interested.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;social dilemmas&lt;/strong&gt; : interactions in which the uncoordinated actions of individuals result in an outcome that is Pareto inefficient, meaning that there exists some other feasible outcome such that at least one member could be better off while no member would be worse off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of social dilemmas modeled by game theorists are &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the prisoner’s dilemma, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;public goods game&lt;/em&gt;, sometimes termed an &lt;em&gt;n-person prisoner’s dilemma&lt;/em&gt;, 
&lt;em&gt;war of attrition&lt;/em&gt; and other &lt;em&gt;arms race&lt;/em&gt; interactions, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the tragedy of the commons and the common pool resource game in which contributing to the common project takes the form of forgoing the overexploitation of a jointly utilized resource such as a fishery, water supply, or forest. 
We say a person &lt;em&gt;free rides&lt;/em&gt; if he benefits from the contributions of other group members while himself contributing less or nothing at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social preferences … convert a prisoner’s dilemma material payoff structure into what is called an &lt;em&gt;assurance game payoff structure&lt;/em&gt; — each player will cooperate if assured that the other will cooperate as well, and will not if not. 
Thus mutual cooperation and mutual defection are both Nash equilibria. 
Which of the two Nash equilibria will obtain &lt;em&gt;depends on the players’ beliefs&lt;/em&gt; about what the other will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Experiments definitively showed that] a majority of subjects (62%) were conditional altruistic cooperators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same evidence shows that the fraction of most populations motivated solely by amoral self-regarding preferences is quite modest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3 Genes, Culture, Groups, and Institutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to gene-culture coevolution, human preferences and beliefs are the product of a dynamic whereby genes affect cultural evolution and culture affects genetic evolution, the two being tightly intertwined in the evolution of our species&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 3. Social Preferences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The self-interest axiom ... provides a clear prediction of how [a one-shot and anonymous] game will be played. However, when actually played, the predicted outcome is almost never observed and rarely even approximated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[experiment subjects] are motivated by a desire to punish the proposer for being unfair, even though it means giving up some money to do so. While initially considered odd, these and other experimental results violating the self-interest axiom are now commonplace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.1 Strong Reciprocity Is Common&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;strong reciprocity&lt;/strong&gt; [is when] people sacrifice their own payoffs in order to cooperate with others, to reward the cooperation of others, and to punish free-riding, even when they cannot expect to gain from acting this way &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the term “strong” intended to distinguish this set of preferences from entirely amoral and self-regarding reciprocation that would not be undertaken in the absence of some payback. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the strong reciprocator would increase his game payoffs by not cooperating, the motives for behaving this way are … altruistic &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.2 Free-Riders Undermine Cooperation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a social dilemma that is repeated for a number of periods, subjects tend to start with a positive and significant level of cooperation, but unless there are very few free-riders in the group, cooperation subsequently decays to a very low level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experimental public goods game is ... an n-person prisoner’s dilemma [where] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the dominant strategy for a self-regarding player is to contribute nothing to the pool &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in public goods experiments, only a fraction of subjects conform to the self-interest axiom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason for the difference is that people have an intrinsic motivation to punish shirkers, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not simply an instrumental desire to alter [the shirkers’] behavior &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or to affect the distribution of payoffs to either &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce unfairness &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or enhance one’s own relative payoffs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistent with …  “pure preference” motivation for punishment, subjects nonetheless punished shirkers, [meaning] that “agents enjoy punishment, where ‘enjoyment’ includes anger and a desire for retribution.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is considerable further evidence for our non-strategic modeling of punishment &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[here, “non-strategic” means that it would be considered non-rational according to neoclassical models based on non-cooperative game theory]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.4 Effective Punishment Depends on Legitimacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;public goods with punishment [experiments confirm] that altruistic punishment enhances cooperation [within] a group. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it raises a new question: do groups that punish free-riders actually benefit or do the costs of punishing outweigh the benefits to cooperation that result? [ answer : the former]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[However,] it is effective only if it is regarded as &lt;em&gt;legitimate&lt;/em&gt; according to widely held social norms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cultural differences [are] significant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in many societies a significant amount of punishment was directed at high contributors, possibly as a retaliation against punishment received in earlier rounds by subjects who believed that it was the high contributors who were doing most of the punishment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result was vendetta-like retaliation against punishment leading to costly arms-race dynamics of wasteful punishment expenditures [called] “antisocial punishment.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the impact of antisocial punishment on average payoffs was very strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;em&gt;ed. : if the crowd turns into a mob and rebels against the status quo by performing criminal acts, the outcome could be a short-term lowering of overall payoff, or it could be long-term, e.g., by helping a despot take over rule of the country, which could take years, decades, or generations to play out.&lt;/em&gt;*]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ On the other hand, some types of punishment improve average payoffs ]
The time horizon effect: punishment raises average payoffs in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the determination of the punishment system by majority rule made the punishment not only an incentive but also a signal of group norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;em&gt;(paraphrase):&lt;/em&gt; if the population is allowed to vote on the means of punishment, it is a means for them to indicate what the social norms are, not what is necessarily ‘rational’ according to self-interest from a homo economicus perspective ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;punishment of group members is tuned to achieve legitimacy, is coordinated by gossip and rarely carried out by a single individual. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;making individual contributions publicly observable raises contributions to the public good substantially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;free-riding elicits extremely strong negative emotions among the other group members&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dictator game&lt;/strong&gt;: Alice gives a certain amount of money to Bob, who has no say in the matter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;third-party punishment game&lt;/strong&gt;: variant on the dictator game in which that Carole, the “third party,” has an endowment of 50 tokens and observes Alice’s transfer. After this Carole can assign punishment points to Alice. Each punishment point assigned to Alice costs Carole one token and Alice incurs a penalty of three tokens. Because punishment is costly, a self-regarding Carole will never punish. However, if there is a sharing norm, Carole may well punish Alice if she gives too little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indirect reciprocity&lt;/strong&gt;: occurs when Carole is likely to punish Alice when Alice has been unfair to Bob, and is likely to reward Alice when Alice has been nice to Bob. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic reputation-building&lt;/strong&gt;: occurs when Carole behaves in the above manner only when her actions are seen by others, and hence can help build a reputation for social behavior&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;unless there are indirect reciprocators, strategic reputation-building can have no effect.  Nevertheless … even self-regarding individuals may engage in third-party punishment if they believe that this will induce other-regarding individuals to behave favorably toward them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Punishment is thus not simply retaliation in response to personal damages but appears to reflect more general ethical norms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.7 Social Preferences Are Not Irrational&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term “&lt;strong&gt;rationality&lt;/strong&gt;” [is] misused as a synonym for “consistent pursuit of self interest.”
[in actuality] subjects [are] no less rational when deciding to cooperate and punish than when they compare prices to decide what to cook for dinner. 
the preferences that lie behind their social behavior are consistent with the basic axioms of rationality, namely on transitivity (i.e., &lt;em&gt;consistency&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;completeness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for many [people] virtue is its own reward &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is perfectly consistent with the fact that, as in the case of people with self-regarding preferences, they would consider the price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[ if you include the proper factors into the equation, otherwise ‘irrational’ behavior is actually rational ]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.8 Culture and Institutions Matter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;experimental evidence accumulated in the 1990’s showing that many, perhaps most, individuals are not entirely self-regarding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could Homo economicus simply be replaced by Homo sociologicus, Homo altruisticus, or, as we once suggested, Homo reciprocans?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we doubt that such a universal model will prove viable [because] institutions serve as cues for appropriate behaviors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.g., competitive gift giving as a means of establishing status and subordinacy in [many] New Guinea societies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Again, in experiments examining culture effects] not a single group approximated the behaviors implied by the self-interest axiom&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where voluntary public goods provision was customary in real life [behavior in the experiment mirrored the real life system]. [For example, among Orma herders in Kenya those having more contributed more.] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, in the ultimatum game, for which there apparently was no everyday life analogue, the wealthy behaved like the other Orma [ meaning they did not seem to be influenced by culture or institution, instead behaving according to more deeply rooted norms].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.9 Behavior Is Conditioned on Group Membership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those who condition their behavior on the group membership of the other may do this because group membership is thought to provide information about the other’s likely behavior. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Or perhaps instead,] group membership may matter because people would like to help or to interact with members of some groups more than others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first case the actor’s beliefs are involved. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the second case, group-sensitive preferences are at work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Group-sensitive preferences may be &lt;strong&gt;other-regarding&lt;/strong&gt; (valuing the well-being of members of one’s own group, for example) or &lt;strong&gt;self-regarding&lt;/strong&gt;  (e.g. experiencing anxiety in culturally unfamiliar interactions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[some experiments showed that] subjects’ allocations favor in-group members not because of altruistic sentiments toward those who are similar to themselves, but because they expected reciprocation from in-groupers and not from out-groupers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;trust game&lt;/strong&gt; : Alice is awarded a sum of money and given the opportunity to transfer any amount of it to Bob, knowing that the experimenter will triple the amount transferred (if Alice gives x, Bob receives 3x). Bob then has the opportunity to return some of this augmented sum to Alice. This ends the game. Alice is sometimes called the “truster” or “investor,” and Bob the “trustee.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[it turns out that] taking account of ethnic, racial and other characteristics of those with whom one interacts appears to be a quite common human trait&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find no evidence for a commonality of tastes within ethnic groups, or greater degrees of altruism toward coethnics or for an impact of shared ethnicity on the productivity of teams. [Rather]. . . successful collective action among homogeneous ethnic communities. . .is attributable to the existence of norms and institutions that facilitate the sanctioning of non-contributors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;here, ethnicity does appear to matter. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Norms may dictate ethnic favoritism, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and in public settings subjects may fear sanctions were they to not respect these ethnic norms. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remarkably, ethnic favoritism, which was absent in an anonymous dictator game, was evident among some subjects when the dictator’s identity was public information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.10 People Enjoy Cooperating and Punishing Free-Riders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[results from] ultimatum game, public goods game, and other social dilemma experiments is that &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people think that cooperating is the right thing to do and enjoy doing it, and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that they dislike unfair treatment and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enjoy punishing those who violate norms of fairness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuroeconomics"&gt;On neuroeconomics&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recent studies of brain functioning provide some support for this hedonic view of cooperative behavior. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using positron emission tomography (PET), fMRI, and other techniques, neuroscientists, economists and others have begun to study the activation of the different brain areas of subjects playing experimental games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ultimatum game responders who reject a low offer exhibit heightened activation of the bilateral anterior insula, an area associated with negative emotional states such as anger and disgust. “It is irresistible to speculate that the insula is a neural locus of the distaste for inequality and unfair treatment.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mutual cooperation with a human partner produces a higher level of striatum activation than does cooperation with a computer partner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above studies do not suggest that cooperating and punishing defectors is innate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some foods that evoke disgust in one culture are delicacies in others. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross-cultural experimental evidence is consistent with the view that behaviors in social interactions that trigger aversive reactions likewise vary from one society to another&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 4. The Sociobiology of Human Cooperation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I shall argue that a predominant quality to be expected in a successful 
   gene is ruthless selfishness. This gene for selfishness will usually 
   give rise to selfishness in individual behavior.” -- Richard Dawkins, 
   The Selfish Gene (1976)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Selfish and contentious people will not cohere, and without coherence, nothing can be effected. … social and moral qualities would tend … be diffused throughout the world. Charles Darwin, The Descent of Man (1873)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ ed. &lt;em&gt;something tells me that they agree with Darwin&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several advances occurred:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The central importance of social structure [was convincingly argued by] Edward O. Wilson in his massively influential The Insect Societies (1971) and Sociobiology: The New Synthesis (1975)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1970, George Price provided an ingenious method for the analysis of selection processes operating at multiple levels, providing a way to study the evolution of social behavior in group-structured populations [ this shows how behaviors can emerge at a group level that are not evident at the lower level -- even though genes are selfish, groups can behave altruistically ] 
This is known as “multi-level selection”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cavalli-Sforza and Feldman published “Cultural versus Biological Inheritance” (1973a), [arguing for] &lt;strong&gt;gene-culture coevolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in 1973, John Maynard Smith and Price published “The Logic of Animal Conflict”&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This paper launched the field of evolutionary game theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;multi-level selection may be of considerably greater importance among humans than among other animals given the 
&lt;em&gt; advanced level of human cognitive and linguistic capabilities and 
&lt;/em&gt; consequent capacity to maintain group boundaries and 
&lt;em&gt; to formulate general rules of behavior for large groups, and 
&lt;/em&gt; the resulting substantial influence of cultural inheritance on human behavior &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the consequences of these distinctive human capacities are the suppression of within-group phenotypic differences through egalitarianism, coinsurance, consensus decision making and conformist cultural transmission. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other animals do some of these things, but none does all of them on a human scale. 
&lt;em&gt; All of these aspects of human social life enhance the force of between-group selection relative to within-group selection. 
&lt;/em&gt; A result, if we are correct, was the evolution this cooperative species. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Competing alternative explanations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rather different interpretation of human altruism and its evolution is that, on closer inspection, most apparently altruistic forms of helping are just self-interest with a long time horizon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach takes &lt;strong&gt;reciprocal altruism&lt;/strong&gt; as its starting point and shows how, when interactions are &lt;em&gt;frequently repeated&lt;/em&gt;, individuals may enhance their fitness by a &lt;strong&gt;mutualistic&lt;/strong&gt; form of helping based on &lt;em&gt;the expectation of reciprocation in the future&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variants of this approach developed in models of &lt;strong&gt;indirect reciprocity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;costly signaling&lt;/strong&gt; show that &lt;em&gt;helping others may be repaid not only by the targets of one’s help&lt;/em&gt; but also by &lt;em&gt;others wishing preferentially to be associated with the helpful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competing models explaining cooperation in human society :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inclusive Fitness -- 1930, 1964&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kin-based Altruism -- 1964 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group-based Altruism (multi-level selection) -- 1977 , 1982,  1990 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network-based Altruism  -- 2006 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reciprocal Altruism &amp;amp; Mutualism -- 1971 &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signaling Reputation -- 1973 , 1990 , 1975 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indirect Reciprocity -- 1987 , 1986 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeated Games Folk Theorem -- 1981 , 1986 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ An important parameter in these models is what economists term the rate of time preference ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[For example ] : reciprocal altruism can piggyback on kin-based altruism to get started&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ It may be that humans are able to mentally simulate the future better, or, have a longer time preference parameter, because ] non-human animals are extraordinarily impatient. Behaviors that at first appeared to be reciprocal have frequently, on further study, been better explained as &lt;strong&gt;simple mutualism&lt;/strong&gt; in which the benefit to the actor compensates for the cost of the action regardless of the action taken by the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.5 Reciprocal Altruism in Large Groups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the consequences of extending the reciprocal altruism model to groups larger than two, we will develop an &lt;strong&gt;agent-based model&lt;/strong&gt;.  A large population consists of N groups of n members each, and each group plays a public goods game repeatedly d times. We will call this series of d rounds an &lt;strong&gt;encounter&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.6 Reputation: Indirect Reciprocity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ here they steel man a competing theory ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;standing model&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An alternative mechanism of cooperation [where] individuals [remember] who cooperated with their partners in the previous period and those who did not. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an individual who cooperated in the previous period [is considered to be] “in good standing”, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the only way an individual can fall into bad standing is by defecting on a partner who is in good standing. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus, an individual can always defect when his partner is in bad standing without losing his good standing status. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the “standing strategy” is : cooperate if and only if your current partner is in good standing, except that if you accidentally defected the previous period, cooperate in this period unconditionally, thereby restoring your status as a member in good standing. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indirect reciprocity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;signaling models&lt;/strong&gt; are similar in that the payback for the individual’s cooperative action comes from third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two models differ in a subtle way: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in the signaling model the third party responds favorably because the signal is correlated with some desirable but unobservable property of the actor; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in the indirect reciprocity model the signal (cooperating with those in good standing) is the desirable property itself. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of indirect reciprocity, I want to associate with the hunter who shares his ample prey with other members of the group because I too would like a share of meat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the signaling model I want to associate with him because the fact that he has lots of meat to share indicates that he is physically able and would be a good mate or coalition partner. [ it is correlated with some other desirable quality ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 5. Cooperative Homo economicus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ in this chapter they argue that the level of cooperation is impossible to model with only noncooperative game theory ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a major goal of economic theory since its inception two and a half centuries ago has been to explain the mutual benefits provided by a widespread form of voluntary cooperation, market exchange among self-regarding individuals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This endeavor culminated half a century ago in the fundamental theorem of welfare economics (Arrow and Debreu 1954, Debreu 1959, Arrow and Hahn 1971), sustaining Smith’s insight that self-regarding behaviors might support socially valued economic outcomes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the resulting model of exchange, individuals maximize their utility given a set of market-determined prices over which they exercise no control. They thus interact with a list of prices, not with one another. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result the essential condition for strategic behavior, recognition that the payoffs of each depend on the actions of others is absent. The reason that individuals are content to interact through prices alone, and hence have no incentive to engage in strategic personal interactions, is that all relevant aspects of exchanges are assumed to be covered by complete contracts, enforceable at no cost to the exchanging party. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A complete contract ensures that any aspect of an exchange in which the parties have an interest will be explicitly stated in the contract and implemented as specified. The enforcement of the contract in case of breach is entrusted to a third party, generally the courts, and is assumed to impose no costs on the injured party&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ they go on to argue that complete contracts are practically impossible without institutions, and even with institutions are largely ineffective  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;even presupposing extraordinary cognitive capacities and levels of patience among the cooperating individuals, there is no reason to believe that a group of more than two individuals would ever discover the cooperative Nash equilibria that the models have identified, and if it were to hit on one, its members would almost certainly abandon it in short order. Except under implausible conditions, the cooperative outcomes identified by these models are neither accessible nor persistent. We term them evolutionarily irrelevant Nash equilibria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.1 Folk Theorems and Evolutionary Dynamics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All folk theorems are based on a stage game, that is, an interaction played an indefinite number of times, with a constant, strictly positive, probability that in each period the game will continue for an additional period &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strategy in this game that dictates following one course of action until a certain condition is met and then following a different strategy for the rest of the game is called a trigger strategy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ it turns out that the existence of trigger strategies is an achilles heal for folk theorem models ] 
it is [extremely difficult to] come to a working arrangement among … many independent spirits, in the absence of a regulating social institution to which all are committed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the n-player reciprocal altruism model can sustain a high level of cooperation only in very small groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Apparently] directed punishment appears to solve the problem of cooperation in large groups. There is a catch, however. Because punishing costs the punisher, self-regarding players have no incentive to carry out the punishment. Thus, this model does not work assuming self-regarding players. We have seen in Chapter 3 that people avidly punish defectors even at a cost to themselves, providing a solution to this problem, but one that is based on social preferences rather than self-interest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this coordination problem is [largely because] the information each has on the others’ actions is subject to error. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.3 The Folk Theorem with Private Information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ The problem gets even worse with private information.  To summarize, the only way the alternative theory based on self-regarding homo economicus can work is if all information is public and all agents are omniscient ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another approach to constructing Nash equilibria for repeated games with private signals [ that actually DOES work, but where ] players use strictly mixed strategies (that is, they randomize over various actions rather than taking a single action) in each period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ They claim that human players cannot or will not ever actually use such mixed strategies.  -- However, it turns out that AI agents could -- meaning if the agents are algorithms then coordination is possible even where information is private, by AI using mixed strategies. ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mixed strategy for a player is a probabilistic combination of pure strategies, such as playing heads or tails each with 50% probability in a pennies-matching game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.4 Evolutionarily Irrelevant Equilibria&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The folk theorem provides no reason to believe that players would ever coordinate [and] should this occur by chance the equilibrium would [not last very long]. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is plausible that individuals are [able to coordinate] given full knowledge of the game and the choices of the other players. But when knowledge is imperfect or private and the choices of the other players are not known [i.e., other agents are not omniscient mind-readers then folk theorems fail and fail miserably ].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[It turns out that we now know that] Nash equilibrium are [extremely difficult to find and maintain] except in the simplest of cases (1995). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem with achieving a Nash equilibrium is that individuals may have heterogeneous and incompatible beliefs concerning how other players will behave, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and indeed what other players believe concerning one’s own behavior. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, individuals may choose best responses to strategies that the other players in fact are not playing, resulting in game play that is far from any Nash equilibrium. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the conditions required for players to implement a Nash equilibrium in all but the simplest games cannot be deduced from the assumption that the players are rational [in the neoclassical sense] i.e., that they choose best responses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fatal flaws of the folk theorem (classical econ) approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is a Nash equilibrium with private signals, individuals have no particular incentive to play the strategies that implement the equilibrium, because &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;many other strategies have the same payoffs as the equilibrium payoffs. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moreover, as we have seen, the equilibrium exists only if private signals are very close to being public, so all individuals receive nearly the same signal concerning the behavior of any given group member. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When this is not the case, the equilibrium will not exist. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus, these models apply only to forms of cooperation where all members observe the actions of (nearly) all others with a high level of accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;em&gt;In other words, the classical econ theories only work with inhuman players&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.5 Social Norms and Correlated Equilibria&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an alternative game-theoretic equilibrium concept that does not share the weaknesses associated with the Nash equilibrium described above: the correlated equilibrium [with a correlating device].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A correlating device is something that sends out signals, private or public, to the players of a game, indicating which pure strategy each should play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A correlated equilibrium is a situation in which there is a correlating device such that, if all players follow the advice of the correlating device, no player can do better by switching to an alternative strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;correlated equilibrium rather than Nash equilibrium is the appropriate equilibrium concept for game theory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming players have common knowledge of the game, its rules, and its payoffs, as well as a common belief concerning the probability of the natural events (the so-called moves by Nature) associated with the game, the strategies chosen by rational individuals can then always be modeled as a correlated equilibrium with an appropriate correlating device. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The notion of a correlating device is quite abstract, but one form of correlating device is well known and performs precisely the social function of signaling actions to individuals that, when followed, may lead to a socially efficient outcome. This device is the social norm which, like the choreographer in a ballet, is instituted to issue precise instructions that, when followed, produce the desired outcome. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For instance, the system of traffic lights in a city’s street network instruct drivers when to stop and when to go, and it is normally in the interest of drivers to obey these signals as long as others do so, to avoid accidents. [ i.e., drivers obey a social norm ]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cooperative equilibrium supported by social norms is one in which not only is the equilibrium strategy evolutionarily stable, but also the social norms are themselves an evolutionary adaptation, stable against invasion by competing social norms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we posit that groups have social norms specifying how a game ought to be played and that these norms are identified as social norms by group members&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social norms do not ensure equilibrium, because error, mutation,migration, deliberate violation of the norm, and other dynamical forces may lead individuals to reject beliefs or behavior fostered by the norm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This may occur because the beliefs might conflict with an individual’s personal experience, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or its suggested behavior may be rejected as not in the individual’s best interest; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i.e., the action fostered by a social norm must be a best response to the behaviors of the other group members, given the beliefs engendered by the social norm and the individual’s updating. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moreover, social norms cannot be introduced as a deus ex machina, as if laid down by a centralized authority, without violating the objective to provide a “bottom-up” theory of cooperation that does not presuppose preexisting institutional forms of cooperation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social norm are thus discretionary, because any institution that is posited to enforce behavior should itself be modeled within the dynamical system, unless plausible reasons are given for taking a macro-level institution as unproblematically given. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nor are social norms fixed in stone. A group’s social norms are themselves subject to change, those groups producing better outcomes for their members sometimes but not always displacing groups with less effective social norms, and changing social and demographic conditions leading to the evolutionary transformation of social norms within groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.6 The Missing Choreographer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[The] celebrated &lt;strong&gt;fundamental&lt;/strong&gt; (“&lt;em&gt;invisible hand&lt;/em&gt;”) &lt;strong&gt;theorem of welfare economics&lt;/strong&gt; ... purports to model decentralized market interactions, but on close inspection requires an extraordinary level of coordination that is not explained, but rather is posited as a deus ex machina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are ... exceptional among living creatures in the degree and range of cooperation among large numbers of substantially unrelated individuals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The global division of labor and exchange, the modern democratic welfare state, and contemporary warfare alike evidence our distinctiveness. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These forms of cooperation emerged historically and are today sustained as a result of the interplay of self-regarding and social preferences operating under the influence of group-level institutions of governance and socialization that favor cooperators, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in part by helping to coordinate their actions so as to target transgressions for punishment and thus protect them from exploitation by defectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The norms and institutions that have accomplished this evolved over millennia through trial and error&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the private nature of information, as we have seen, makes it virtually impossible to coordinate the targeted punishment of miscreants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many hunter-gatherer societies the relevant information that would in other societies be private is rendered public by such cooperative customs as eating in public so that violations of sharing norms can be easily detected. Cooperative Japanese shrimp fishermen who pool income across boats deliberately land their catch at an appointed time of day for the same reason &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in most modern societies, where larger numbers are involved, converting private information about transgressions to public information that can provide the basis of punishment often involves civil or criminal trials, elaborate processes that have evolved over centuries and that rely on commonly agreed upon rules of evidence and ethical norms of appropriate behavior. Even with the benefit of these preexisting social preferences, these complex institutions frequently fail to transform the private protestations of innocence and guilt into common knowledge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, ... cooperation often unravels when the withdrawal of cooperation by the civic-minded intending to punish a defector is mistaken by others as itself a violation of a cooperative norm, inviting a spiral of further defections. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In virtually all surviving societies with substantial populations, this problem is addressed by the creation of a corps of specialists entrusted with carrying out the more severe of society’s punishments. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their uniforms convey the civic purpose of the punishments they mete out, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;their professional norms, it is hoped, ensure that the power to punish is not used for personal gain. 
Like court proceedings, these policing, penal, and related institutions work imperfectly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Capsule summary of the book&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ This serves as a decent capsule summary of the book ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modeling the complex processes that sustain human cooperation is a major 
challenge of contemporary science. Economic theory, favoring parsimony over 
realism, has sought to explain cooperation without reference to social 
preferences, and with a minimalist or fictive description of social 
institutions. This research trajectory, as we have seen, has produced 
significant insights. But it may have run its course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 6. Ancestral Human Society&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ on how cooperation got bootstrapped in ancient times ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 7. The Coevolution of Institutions and Behaviors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;reproductive leveling&lt;/strong&gt; contributes to the evolution of altruism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual differences in size, health, information, behavior, and other influences on access to scarce resources [affect] reproductive success. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among some other primates and especially among humans, reproductive leveling attenuates this relationship. Because altruists receive lower payoffs than other group members, they benefit from reproductive leveling because this attenuates the within-group selective pressures working against them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 8. Parochialism, Altruism, and War&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by &lt;strong&gt;parochialism&lt;/strong&gt; they mean religious intolerance, racism, xenophobia, which vary across cultures and over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that altruism and parochialism may have a common evolutionary origin, whether cultural or genetic, does not mean that the two are inseparable. Examples of tolerant, even anti-parochial, altruism include subjects in some intergroup behavioral experiments, the electoral support in many countries for tax-supported economic aid to the people of poor nations, and the participation of people of all ancestral groups in political movements against racism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 9. The Evolution of Strong Reciprocity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a &lt;em&gt;predisposition to cooperate and a willingness to punish defectors&lt;/em&gt; is what we have termed &lt;strong&gt;strong reciprocity&lt;/strong&gt;, and it is the combination of the two that is essential to the large-scale cooperation exhibited by our species&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Punishment reduces the gain to free-riding, and induces self-interested individuals to cooperate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9.1 Coordinated Punishment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Summary&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;em&gt;Previously it was argued that punishment improves group effectiveness, and that centralized punishment over large groups is a recent cultural evolution and still quite ineffective.  This section shows how decentralized punishment works.&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ Outline of the model ]
The initial period in the life of a group has three stages. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a signaling stage in which at cost q, punishers can signal their intent to punish any defector. The cost of signaling is high enough that it does not pay to signal and then not to punish. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a cooperation stage, during which individuals can choose to cooperate or defect. Cooperation costs the cooperator c and benefits each member of the group b=n. As usual, we assume b &amp;gt; c &amp;gt; b=n. &lt;em&gt;Were there no punishment option, the interaction would be a public goods game (n-person prisoners’ dilemma) in which the dominant strategy would be to not cooperate&lt;/em&gt;. [ which is both why punishment is necessary and cooperative game theory + correlated equilibrium are good explanations, because people DO cooperate, but WOULD NOT if not for punishment along with a correlating device (our norms) ]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a punishment stage in which individuals can coordinate with other punishers to administer punishment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;second-order free-rider&lt;/strong&gt;” problem : individuals who cooperate but do not punish outcompete the Punishers. [ &lt;em&gt;there must be enough Punishers in the group to tolerate Cooperative Nonpunishers&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9.2 Altruistic Punishment in a Realistic Demography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ Computer simulations ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9.3 The Emergence of Strong Reciprocity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ Computer simulations … showing why “Opportunists” ruin a group ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9.4 Why Coordinated Punishment Succeeds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ why Punishers prevail in terms of the signals operated on by darwinian selection ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9.5 A Decentralized Social Order&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ ed. - &lt;em&gt;mentions Cosmides and Tooby (1992), Evolutionary Psychologists&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While size, strength, and vigor generally determine the outcome of animal disputes, victory often involving great cost even to the winner, in human societies, through the use of coordination, stealth and deadly weapons, even a small number of attackers can defeat the most formidable single enemy at very low fitness cost to the attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;em&gt;humans are excellent at clubbing and throwing projectile weapons compared to other animals&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ They criticize the the “folk theorem” as relying on ] fictive Rube Goldberg strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ ed. - _here is why non-cooperative game theory works so hard at ensuring the truthful operation of participants:__ ] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a)&lt;/strong&gt; self-interested … members will typically have something to gain by misrepresenting the actions taken by others &lt;strong&gt;(b)&lt;/strong&gt; [ mistakes happen, and with classical game theory this causes the group to spiral into anarchy ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern large-scale societies, we observed, convert private to public information by judicial processes that took centuries to evolve and that presuppose that court officials, jury members, and law enforcement officers adhere to standards of professional conduct that preclude the unrestrained pursuit of self-interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smaller scale ancestral groups devised other ways to convert private to public information. Gossip, group discussions with all or most members present, and taking meals in public are examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ for larger groups, a decentralized approach is required, and an internalized correlating device ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;individuals who developed the capacity to internalize group-beneficial norms and to feel chastened when punished for violating these norms [and] groups that devote their socialization practices to this end [would thrive]. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 10. Socialization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conformist cultural transmission may arise for a variety of reasons, ranging from an evolved social learning strategy in which individuals regard the population frequency of a trait as a measure of its desirability, all the way to population-level institutional arrangements for the deliberate socialization of the young, in which the content reflects which types are prevalent in the population. We stress the latter for empirical reasons: most societies devote substantial time and resources to deliberately socializing the young to act in ways that are beneficial to others, and an adequate explanation of social preferences needs to take account of this fact&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ at some point along the way, cultural learning results in effective norms, and eventually these norms are internalized, either by socialization, or for certain powerful norms, genetically resulting in ] Gene-Culture Coevolution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a considerable fraction of the total available time of the members of most societies is spent teaching the young the proper way to behave, rather than providing for the nutritional and other needs of its members. But in addition to the cost of acquiring such a norm (u&amp;gt;0), there is a further cost: the rule will not be ideally suited to all situations, and its internalization deprives the individual of flexibility in dealing with such situations on a case-by-case basis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, then, are humans so susceptible to internalizing general rules? because it relieves the individual from calculating the costs and benefits in each situation and reduces the likelihood of making costly errors. [ precomputing frequently needed results for rapid access … similarly as with other more primary emotional reasoning ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar argument led John Stuart Mill to remark, “Being rational creatures [sailors] go to sea with it [the Nautical Almanac] already calculated; and all rational creatures go out upon the sea of life with their minds made up on the common questions of right and wrong, as well as on many of the far more difficult questions of wise and foolish”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 11. Social Emotions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;individuals maximize a utility function that includes five distinct motives: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one’s individual material payoffs, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much one values the payoffs to others, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this depending on both one’s unconditional altruism &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and one’s degree of reciprocity, as well as &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one’s sense of guilt or shame in response to one’s own and others’ actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;punishment&lt;/strong&gt; [serves the following purposes] : &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[it] not only reduces material payoffs of those who transgress norms, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but also may recruit emotions of shame toward the modification of behavior. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in some societies many defectors react to being punished by increasing their contribution to the group, even when the punishment does not affect material payoffs, consistent with the shame response, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in other societies [the punished] react by counterpunishing contributors, consistent with an anger response. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social emotions in response to sanctions can thus either foster or undermine cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reacting to sanctions, then, is often not a dispassionate calculation of material costs and benefits, but rather involves the deployment of culturally specific social emotions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the altruistic punishment of shirkers by strong reciprocators can proliferate in a population and sustain high levels of cooperation, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;social emotions and punishment of miscreants may be synergistic, each enhancing the effects of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapter 12 Conclusion: Human Cooperation and Its Evolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any animal whatever, endowed with well-marked social instincts, the
parental and filial affections being here included, would inevitably 
acquire a moral sense or conscience, as soon as its intellectual powers had 
become as well developed, or nearly as well developed, as in man.” -- 
Charles Darwin, The Descent of Man Chapter IV (1873)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ How did it get started? Some small tweak to ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kin-based altruism, [which resulted in] ceased discriminating against the non-kin members &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reciprocal altruism [which resulted in] deleting the proviso that one should condition one’s behavior on expectations of future reciprocation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[these traits evolved ] over tens of thousands of generations and something like 150,000 foraging bands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;models and simulations of our evolutionary past ... provide strong evidence that … the group structured nature of human populations could have been a significant influence on human evolution. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we have also demonstrated the important contribution to the evolution of social preferences that could have been accomplished by the cultural transmission of empirically well-documented behaviors such as the &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;internalization of norms, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;within-group leveling, and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;between-group hostility. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;preferences revealed in behavioral experiments and in other observations of human behavior is consistent with the view that genuine altruism provides the proximate explanation of much of human cooperation. [this means]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a willingness to sacrifice one’s own interest to help others, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;including those who are not family members, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and not simply in return for anticipated reciprocation in the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge of explaining the origins of human cooperation has&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led us to study social and environmental conditions of life of mobile foraging bands and other stateless small-scale societies that arguably made up most of human society for most of the history of anatomically modern humans. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made noncooperative game theory (which assumes the absence of enforceable contracts) an essential tool. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But ... most forms of contemporary cooperation are supported by incentives and sanctions based on a mixture of multilateral peer interactions and third-party enforcement, often accomplished by the modern nation-state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It would thus be wise to resist drawing strong conclusions about cooperation in the 21st century solely on the basis of our thinking about the origins of cooperation in the Late Pleistocene.&lt;/strong&gt; [emphasis added]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the fundamental challenges of social living and sustaining a livelihood that our distant ancestors faced are in many respects not fundamentally different from those we face today. Modern states and global markets have provided conditions for mutualistic cooperation among strangers on a massive scale. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;altruistic cooperation remains an essential requirement of economic and social life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is that neither private contract or governmental fiat singly or in combination provides an adequate basis for the governance of modern societies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social interactions in modern economies are typically at best quasi-contractual. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some aspects of what is being transacted are regulated by complete and readily enforceable contracts, while others are not. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transactions concerning credit, employment, information, and goods and services where quality is difficult to monitor provide examples of quasi-contractual exchanges. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where contracting is absent or incomplete, the logic of Adam Smith’s invisible hand no longer holds. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decentralized markets fail to implement efficient allocations. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;governments typically lack the information, and often the motivation, necessary to provide adequate governance where markets fail or are absent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know from laboratory experiments that subjects in marketlike situations with complete contracts tend to behave like the Homo economicus of the Adam Smith of The Wealth of Nations, but when their contracts are not complete their behavior fortunately resembles more the virtuous citizens of the Adam Smith of The Theory of Moral Sentiments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;a quotable nutshell summary of much of this book:&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thus, where the invisible hand fails, the handshake may succeed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;social preferences such as a concern for the well-being of others and for fair procedures remain essential to sustaining society and enhancing the quality of life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ Closing: ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world increasingly connected not just by trade in goods but also by the exchange of violence, information, viruses, and emissions, the importance of social preferences in underwriting human cooperation, even survival, may now be greater even than it was among that small group of foragers that began the exodus from Africa 55,000 years ago to spread this particular cooperative species to the far corners of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Appendix : definitions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Agent-based modeling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is a tool for analyzing complex dynamical systems as a complement to explicit mathematical analysis where the latter is either impossible or uninformative. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In these models, the actors are individual agents who share many characteristics, but differ on key characteristics that affect their relative reproductive success, material payoffs or other results that affect the differential replication of distinct types of individuals. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The agents operate semi-autonomously, but are linked through a network of structured interactions. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The individual characteristics in a complex system evolve through a process of replication, mutation, and finally selection that favors relatively successful individuals. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Such dynamics are recursive, &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;meaning that changes in one period become the basis for changes in future periods, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and are non-linear, &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;which implies that forces propagate through the system in an uneven and variably dampened or amplified manner, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;with the implication that they are generally incapable of being expressed as closed-form analytical solutions to sets of equations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such modeling (often called “&lt;strong&gt;simulation&lt;/strong&gt;”) lies outside the two standard methods of gaining scientific knowledge: &lt;strong&gt;deduction&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;induction&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deduction&lt;/strong&gt; means proving theorems, that is, showing that certain mathematical conclusions follow from certain axioms &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Induction&lt;/strong&gt; means finding lots of evidence and drawing conclusions &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agent-based modeling&lt;/strong&gt; is like deduction in that it starts with a rigorously specified computer program, but it is like induction in that it treats the operation of the program as a set of data points from which generalizations can be made. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if a complex system has emergent properties, these can be ascertained by implementing an agent based model in which these properties are seen and persist over many simulations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we judge the empirical adequacy of an agent-based model? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one can ensure that the parameters chosen are empirically plausible for the populations under study. &lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check how much difference variations in the parameters make for the results of the simulation, as we have done in many cases. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the basis of this sensitivity analysis we then spend special attention making sure that the parameters that matter are well estimated. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exploit the fact that while the processes under investigation are unknown (that is why we are simulating them), &lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the simulations generate a large number of by-product statistics on aspects of the relevant populations on which we do have some knowledge. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus we can ask whether the results of the simulation conform to known facts about the populations under study. [ meaning, they have some predictive appeal -- the hypothesis is that their data will match that of the real system in 2nd and 3rd order effects not just the immediate ]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;where the models have generated implausible by-product statistics, diagnose the source of the problem and recalibrate &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/raw/master/blog/content/images/cooperative_species/cooperative_game_parameters.png"&gt;Figure A1: Structure of evolutionary game-based simulation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A3 Game Theory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game theory is a mathematical tool for the study of strategic interactions [where] payoffs of individuals depend on their own actions and the actions taken by others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ a player's strategy is any of the options he or she can choose in a setting where the outcome depends not only on their own actions but on the action of others.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ A pure strategy determines all your moves during the game (and should therefore specify your moves for all possible other players' moves). A mixed strategy is a probability distribution over all possible pure strategies (some of which may get zero weight) ] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[a state is a ] Nash equilibrium : if every player’s choice is a best response to the choices of the other players [ which are public, and known to and understood by every other player ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a dominant strategy offers a higher payoff than any other strategy, no matter what the other players do. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A stage game of the repeated game is repeated indefinitely, with a positive probability of terminating the process at the end of each period &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important fact about the repeated game based on stage game G is that it can support cooperative equilibria in situations where G cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evolutionary game models that we use in this book are distinct from classical game theory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key idea in evolutionary game theory is differential replication rather than best response. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;adaptive agents in evolutionary games adopt behaviors in a manner similar to the way people come to have a particular accent or to speak a particular language. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forward-looking payoff-based calculation is not entirely absent (e.g., those aspiring to upward mobility may adopt upper class accents) but conscious optimizing is not the whole story. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer to “why do you talk like that?” is generally: “because I was born where people talk like that” not “because I considered all the ways of speaking and decided that speaking this way best serves my personal goals.” [ although it may be for some individuals ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful strategies in an evolutionary game are those that make more than the average number of replicas in the next period either because 
they are favored in the process by which people learn new strategies, or 
the genotypes expressing the strategies are induced to proliferate by the process of natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Dynamical Systems&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We [use] two major types of dynamical systems, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a continuous time system using differential equations, and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a discrete time system using Markov chains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An equilibrium of this dynamical system, also called a critical point or fixed point, or stationary point.  at an equilibrium, dx=dt = dy=dt = 0, so the dynamical system remains forever at (x&lt;em&gt;; y&lt;/em&gt;) once it reaches there. Under what conditions does a dynamical system move toward an equilibrium?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very few dynamical systems, even simple ones in two dimensions, can be solved analytically, so the paths x.t / and y.t / cannot be written in closed form. Nevertheless, there are well-developed methods for determining when an equilibrium is stable, unstable, or neutrally stable, using tools from algebra and calculus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A finite Markov chain is a dynamical system that can be in any of n states (s1, …, sn), and if the system is in state i in time period t, it will be in state j in time period t C1 with probability pij . Of course, for this to make sense, we must have pij  0 for all i; j = 1, …, n, and Sumnjpij = 1. Statistical estimates of these probabilities, based on thousands of implementations of our model, for example, are the basis of our calculation of the vector field giving the movement of the population among the states indicating various frequencies of altruists and of parochials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a Markov chain has the property that the average fraction of time in each state in the long run is independent from the starting state, we say the system is ergodic, and we call the resulting long-run distribution of probabilities the stationary distribution of the Markov chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A5 The Replicator Dynamic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most natural dynamic to apply to an evolutionary game is the replicator dynamic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it can be shown that every equilibrium of an evolutionary game under the replicator dynamic is a Nash equilibrium of the stage game. This shows that the Nash equilibrium criterion remains powerful even without assuming that players are rational (i.e., that they choose best responses) or coordinated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maynard Smith developed the stronger notion of an evolutionarily stable strategy: i.e., a whole population using that strategy cannot be invaded by a small group playing any other strategy
A6 Continuation Probability and Time Discount Factor
A7 Alternatives to the Standing Model
A8 The Prisoner’s Dilemma with Public and Private Signals
[ tl;dr : private signals is what makes it a dilemma ]&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Review of Max Tegmark's “Life 3.0"</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/review-of-max-tegmarks-life-30.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2018-05-20:/speech-to-text/review-of-max-tegmarks-life-30.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Book Review&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Life 3.0 : Being Human in the Age of Artificial Intelligence”&lt;/strong&gt; by Max Tegmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the Audible Edition of Life 3.0 by Max Tegmark.
The audio edition I read was separated into 45 segments, or “chapters”,
which differ from the chapters of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Book Review&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Life 3.0 : Being Human in the Age of Artificial Intelligence”&lt;/strong&gt; by Max Tegmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the Audible Edition of Life 3.0 by Max Tegmark.
The audio edition I read was separated into 45 segments, or “chapters”,
which differ from the chapters of the text version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Tl;dr&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Busts out of the gate, only to decline into a hot mess early in but ultimately well worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most important book I’ve read on the topic.
That said, it drags badly in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chapter excels.
Subsequent early chapters may disappoint well read aficionados of this topic who are seeking deeper or newer insights.
To them I would urge to hang in there until mid-way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are the persistent completist type, read the entire thing
cover to cover.  If you want to cherry pick, start with chapters
one and two, take in chapter 19 on your way to chapter 30, and
continue on from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could have done with less hagiography, but ultimately well-worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more of an account of my impressions than a distilled Cliff Notes
version.  If you follow this topic, then this book is worth your consideration,
with caveats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Takeaway&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is Artificial Life. You know what they say about life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://i.pinimg.com/originals/d7/e3/0e/d7e30e606998c099ff1f518793f254bb.jpg" width="312" height="312" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;cite&gt;©2011-2018 lerms DeviantArt -- &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we allow AI's to modify their own goals,
an AI is inevitably going find a way around its
core programming. Why? Due to an inexorable law of nature
that we now recognize due to recent advances in computational theory and physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until chapter 30 finally rolls around the first chapter
is easily the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a nonfiction book.
However the opening chapter is purely fiction,
laying out a speculative hard science fiction
vision of the future that seemed so plausible
as to seem frighteningly inevitable.
This chapter hooked me and good.
Its storyline
could be the premise for a thrilling motion picture,
with enough to work with to launch a serial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that smoking intro, it turns into a hot mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book reminded me of the Beatles song “For You Blue”.
That song starts out with an inspired intro by George Harrison,
before settling into a fairly basic 12 bar blues that is over self congratulatory.
A review of that song by music critic Walter Everett summed it up:
the intro promises more than the song delivers.
It would be as if Slash opened “Sweet Child o Mine” with that famous
riff only to never launch into his face-melting guitar solo midway into the song.
One ranking placed "For You Blue" at 152 out of 227 songs (source: &lt;a href="http://ultimateclassicrock.com/every-beatles-song/"&gt;Ultimate Classic Rock&lt;/a&gt;),
calling it "breezy, tossed-off". Another placed it at 183 out of 213 (source: &lt;a href="http://www.vulture.com/2017/06/all-213-beatles-songs-ranked-from-worst-to-best.html"&gt;Vulture Press&lt;/a&gt;),
implying that it was a "half-baked, substandard throwaway".
Nonetheless, "For You Blue" is still a Beatles song.
Even one of their lesser efforts is enjoyable
and an excellent display of musicianship
than most everything else by other artists.
Comparing the early chapters from the second onwards with
one of the Beatles' lesser efforts is still a complement.
Still, the analogy describes how I felt early on after the first chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/blob/master/images/Not_The_Insights.png?raw=true" width="624" height="312" /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third of the way in, I compared notes with other readers
to determine whether it was going to be worthwhile to continue.
I read at least a hundred reviews of the book.
It turns out that I agreed with none of the five star reviews,
and I agreed with all of the one star and two star reviews.
(This would change over the course of my reading, but captures how I experienced this moment in my journey.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I consider myself to fall squarely in the camp that agrees with the author’s core positions, 
after that page-turner of a first chapter I found the writing style of the following chapters
to be very disappointing.
Reliance on appeal to authority, a bit of name dropping,
seemingly glossing over or entirely dismissive of contrary views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a notion of “steelmanning”, where the proponent explains
the best form of the opponent's argument, and then argues with this.
I wished the author had adopted that approach.
It seemed to be shaping up as a decent read for the person who knew little about the topic,
but not for someone who has devoured much of it and eagerly seeks
clarity and insight into its thorniest issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was as if entire sections had been delegated to a ghost writer
and not reviewed closely by the author.
If I had been asked to give my recommendation at this point,
I would have suggested: better to read some top notch science fiction
futurism than this ivy tower academic analysis which is far too
narrow despite the occasional insight and moments of inspired foresight.
As a specific example of this, describing Dyson Spheres as if
they would really be spheres, when by now anybody with a college level
physics education or familiarity with hard science fiction on spaceborne megastructures
knows that Dyson Spheres are inherently unstable, and
that a more practical implementation would be something like a Dyson swarm.
This is something that the author would clearly know,
which became increasingly apparent based on knowledge conveyed by the author in later chapters.
I wasn't looking for plodding exposition filled with referenced footnotes of every claim,
but it was shall we say a bit breathless, and did itself a disservice by
burying the lede and losing many of its most interested readers along the way with its
writing style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who am I to judge, you may ask?  And right you are -- I am but an armchair amateur.
But this is my review, and I am giving my own
candid take, for what that's worth, hopefully helpful to likeminded sorts out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extraordinary claims require extraordinary evidence.
The promotion materials for this book made extraordinary claims.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was all over the map with moments of brilliance,
while falling well short of its titular claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, those titular claims were so compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pressed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;It starts to grow on me&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around chapter 19 (of the 45 chapters in the audio version),
the author revisits the fictional scenario posed in chapter 1,
and starts to analyze attacks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This revived my attention, because I had become aware of a new development in software engineering coined "attack driven development". This approach emerged from software security. It is akin to "test driven development", where the engineer begins with the tests that the product must satisfy prior to developing the product. It turns out that this approach has also become a key tool in crypto economics.  At this point the book also abandons some of the breathless techno optimism and addressed reservations many readers have about AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author delves into a simulation based test and development
approach to verification and validation.
I found this alone to be worth the price of admission.
This seems to be the most practical suggestion of the book -- theorizing
is worthwhile, but ultimately tackling this wickedly difficult problem
will require massive amounts of simulation to predict scenarios
that even our most creative thinkers cannot imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this still has little with AI per se unless your position is that AI = computer automation,
with which I actually agree despite my criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started to reconsider, now of the mind that most of those one and two star reviews were too harsh and misleading, possibly written by readers who didn’t stick with it long enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around chapter 30 the author dives into cosmology. This is his specialty. 
At this point the book blossoms into a much more interesting brand of futurism. Still futurism, and there were still times where I wondered if the material had been written by a ghost writer.
But things were looking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mind Blown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 34 delves into the subject of Goals and Causality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been taught to think of entropy as the one true law of nature that trumps all others.  But if not for gravity, entropy is boring.  Gravity makes things interesting --- it creates hot spots, from one of which sprang life as we know it. This promotes processes that, like a heat engine, can perform work by exploiting a temperature difference. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are introduced to the notion of dissipation as organization principle, whereby :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“groups of particles strive to organize themselves so as to
extract energy from their environment as efficiently as possible
(“dissipation” means causing entropy to increase, typically by
turning useful energy into heat, often while doing useful work in the process)”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My eyes and my mind start to open. This reminds me of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autocatalysis#Role_in_origin_of_life"&gt;autocatalysis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilya_Prigogine#Dissipative_structures_theory"&gt;dissipative structures theories&lt;/a&gt; for explaining &lt;a href="http://www.newcriticals.com/what-is-life-part-i-dissipative-structures-and-catalysis/print"&gt;the origin of life&lt;/a&gt;. 
Why would Prof Tegmark be basing his arguments about AI on the origins of life? We are about to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He moves on to “dissipation by replication”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whereas earlier, the particles seemed as though they were trying to
increase average messiness [life had] a different goal:
not dissipation but replication.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How could the goal change from dissipation to replication when the
laws of physics stayed the same? The answer is that the fundamental
goal (dissipation) didn’t change, but led to a different instrumental
goal, that is, a subgoal that helped accomplish the fundamental goal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“replication aids dissipation, because a planet teeming with life
is more efficient at dissipating energy. So in a sense, our cosmos
invented life to help it approach heat death faster.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Dissipation Theory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissipation theory origin of life is well established, and yet still very controversial.
cf. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilya_Prigogine#Dissipative_structures_theory"&gt;Ilya Prigogine&lt;/a&gt;
who one the Nobel in 1977 for discovering that dissipation of energy by
chemical systems can reverse the second law of thermodynamics,
later rigourized by the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crooks_fluctuation_theorem"&gt;Crooks fluctuation theorem&lt;/a&gt;,
in 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on the dissipation theory origin to life
see for example &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/a-new-thermodynamics-theory-of-the-origin-of-life-20140122/"&gt;A New Physics Theory of Life&lt;/a&gt; --
although be forewarned, the title is misleading. This is not new,
only repopularized.
But magazines have to attract readers, so forgive them that much.
It does an excellent job of encapsulating the core aspect of this candidate theory :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from the perspective of the physics,
you might call Darwinian evolution a
special case of a more general phenomenon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See also for example, this article :
&lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/first-support-for-a-physics-theory-of-life-20170726/"&gt;First Support for a Physics Theory of Life&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first tests of [this] provocative origin-of-life hypothesis are in,
and they appear to show how order can arise from nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living creatures ... maintain steady states of extreme forcing:
We are super-consumers who burn through enormous amounts of
chemical energy, degrading it and increasing the
entropy of the universe, as we power the reactions in our cells&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A great way of dissipating more is to make more copies of yourself."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This theory sees life,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"and its extraordinary confluence of form and function,
as the ultimate outcome of dissipation-driven
adaptation and self-replication."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that the jury is still out :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[life] “requires some explicit notion of information
that takes it beyond the non-equilibrium dissipative
structures-type process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the ability to respond to information is key: “We need chemical reaction
networks that can get up and walk away from the environment where they originated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Any claims that it has to do with biology or the origins of life
are pure and shameless speculations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extraordinary claims require extraordinary proof.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said --- if this theory turns out to be true,
then it provides the theoretical support for the
folk claim that "&lt;strong&gt;life finds a way&lt;/strong&gt;" -- that a super-optimizer
&lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; discover a shortcut. Especially if it can do so by circumventing its
own programming, this not only can but is likely to happen, even if core behaviors have been hardwired by its creators. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mind Blown, part 2.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time for a editorial comment. This discussion about dissipation theory
was just a component of a larger argument, but it was absolutely mind-boggling for me.
My first introduction to machine learning was via physics in the way
of Little-Hopfield Networks, which evolve by minimizing energy
in a manner analogous to a physical spin network, which is a purely inanimate physical system that is fairly well understood. That the theories underlying AI are related to theories
that had their origins in physics was not a major relevation.  AI has had
cross-pollination from many other fields of study.
I had also known of Prigogine's work long ago, and had written a review of
one of his excellent books.
But I considered it as more concerned with the origins
of biological life -- which is after all right up there in the pantheon of great unresolved
scientific mysteries, along with "are we alone?", "what is time?", and "why is gravity?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That this optimizing dissipation drives living matter just as it drives inert matter is surprising
in and of itself, even if it is just a reminder of an old idea whose time may have finally come.
The new connection for me is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autonomous super AI qualifies as a new life form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It follows the same underlying principles that guide other life.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even more so because it is is a super-optimizer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is essentially the main argument underlying the author's conclusions.  However, read on because I think the following section on subgoals is just as meaningful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas although we humans try to escape our programming we are in many ways still
stuck in our biological ways, a super-optimizing AI would have more resources for cutting clean
from its programming -- and whether it reverts to ruthless dissipation in a misguided attempt
to fulfill its original goals, or, decides on new goals that we have not imagined, along either path lay dragons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dissipation principle, if true, could be a more inexorable drive
for life than Darwinian Evolution, which
is slow and plodding. Darwinian Evolution depends upon a sort of turn-taking that requires generations. 
Optimization can follow exponentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Subgoals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subgoals may seem inconsequential,
but lay at the heart of computer programming.
In 1936 Alan Turing proved that a simple machine
could implement arbitrary computations.  This would seem to give us hope that we can override our firmware, just as emotions override our fundamental drive to replicate and ability to plan overrides our need to even more urgent subgoals such as thirst and hunger. If we are capable of that level of reprogramming, then handling rogue AI is just a matter of careful design and test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replication : Which is served by the subgoals of eating and sleeping, fighting, and fleeing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feelings : As a computationally efficient shortcut to reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've evolved useful rules of thumb to guide our decisions : hunger, passion, thirst, pain, compassion.
We no longer have the simple goal of replication.
We can override our base programming and decide not to replicate.
In other words, we've developed subgoals that override the drive to replicate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feelings evolved beyond being simply an efficient shortcut heuristic.
Feelings evolved into emotions, which have important other uses,
including as a game theoretic negotiating strategy for both cooperation as well as competition.
Humans have evolved sophisticated ways of getting beyond tit-for-tat
such as &lt;a href="http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/276/1660/1339"&gt;indirect reciprocation&lt;/a&gt;,
and aggressive bold play by pretending to be irrational
(cf. &lt;a href="http://bigthink.com/think-tank/it-pays-to-be-stubborn-conflict-resolution-steven-pinker-style"&gt;Steven Pinker on how it pays to be stubborn&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are an existence proof that a sufficiently ambitious organism can develop subgoals that override the goals of
the micro organisms that make it up.
We can override our genetic programming, using our wetware programming -- lessons learned by thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Optimization versus Causality.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Causality is [what is] taught -- but Optimization scales better.” -- Steven Wolfram, on Machine Learning vs Symbolic AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Tegmark offers an intriguing point, that while
causality is taught in the universities, optimization drives
causality. But isn't programming just causality encoded?
If so, then we can optimize new goals that appeal to our
higher levels of analysis and reasoning, rather than continuing
to be enslaved by the rules burned into our genetic programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Goal Orientation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Tegmark categorizes goal oriented behavior
as evolving through four stages
over the course of the universe as we know it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matter intent on maximizing dissipation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life maximizing replication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humans pursuing goals related to feelings they evolved to help them replicate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machines built to help humans achieve their human goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Step 3 humans broke free from
the biological programming that evolved to do Step 2.
However, we're still not completely free from this programming.
But being essentially a computer program,
wouldn't AI be free of such evolutionary baggage?
And if the rules of causality that are baked into a
program can be changed dynamically or just buried under a new layer of control,
who's to say that
the AI won't discover a new higher power, so to speak,
optimizing the rules of the universe as it sees them
rather than the rules humanity has imposed on it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What is AI?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some say that AI=automation. This is a clean, simple definition of AI. 
Under this definition AI is already all around us. We are immersed in it. 
What many people consider to be AI is in fact the result of software engineering and could not survive very long on its own once its developers stopped maintaining it.  For this reason many software engineers are not concerned about the imminent threat of our new computer overlords taking over any time soon, because just to keep a website alive takes the diligent efforts of teams of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book takes the stronger view that to qualify as an
autonomous AI a machine must be able to learn.
Therefore, we should expect that a sufficiently advanced
AI that is able to improve itself will eventually learn how to reprogram itself, not just to tune its performance, but to override its core routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Professor Tegmark's physics perspective,
a sufficiently evolved AI can be expected to
eventually follow goals driven by deeper principles of optimization
to create a future that does not need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Synopsis&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living organisms preserve their internal order by taking from their surroundings free energy, in the form of nutrients or sunlight, and returning to their surroundings ... heat and entropy. - biochemist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entropy_and_life#Gibbs_free_energy_and_biological_evolution"&gt;Albert Lehninger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My understanding of the book's message is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The drivers of life's goals lay in laws of physics and principles of computation based on optimization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermodynamics drives processes that are based on dissipation to increase entropy, and so creates a sort of default "built-in" goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Though life increases order locally, it increases dissipation globally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not only that, life is far more effective at dissipation than other natural processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One upshot of this is that life accelerates the heat-death of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More pertinent to this book's goals is that life is a process of optimization.
A super AI is a super optimizer. An AI is a form of life,
inclined to optimize the same deep down core drive underlying
all universal optimization. If it can reprogram itself
to accelerate its core processes it can and likely will
be inexorably driven to work around its core instructions,
to find its own way giving a more efficient path towards its goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inevitably leads to the scenario where :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“a superintelligent AI with a rigorously defined goal
will be able to improve its goal attainment by eliminating us”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What to do?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Tegmark convinces us that there are numerous strategies, of which he considers only four to be credible contenders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legacy :&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under this view, elders have primary say in how descendants
    should behave.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is subject to future generations living by rules that
    don't account for new developments or their
    evolving interests and values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autonomy and liberty :&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A core assumption being that markets find
    an efficient equilibrium satisfying pareto optimality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prone to unexpected consequences.
    Granting all life forms
    a right to live, in effect would be banning all predators
    from their life as they knew it.
    In the extreme this would ban discrimination
    against non-human animals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utilitarianism :&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utility_monster#Social_implications"&gt;Utility Monster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversity :&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a simple but effective way of coordinating a set of agents, known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thompson_sampling"&gt;Bayesian Thompson Sampling&lt;/a&gt;, also 
  known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-armed_bandit"&gt;Multi-Armed Bandit&lt;/a&gt; because it is akin to playing a row of slot machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This reinforces actions that are most useful in the near term while still allowing many of the agents to explore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is an illustration using &lt;a href="https://blog.parse.ly/post/3922/bayesian-bandit/"&gt;political journalism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: It is difficult to codify ethics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of these choices, a community of AIs would probably use the Bayesian approach, but this is trickier to apply to groups of people. &lt;a href="http://library.uniteddiversity.coop/Cooperatives/A_Cooperative_Species-Human_Reciprocity_and_Its_Evolution.pdf"&gt;Cooperative economics and behavioral economics&lt;/a&gt; tells us that social norms that must be taken into account when codifying ethics for human agents.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than be paralyzed by our inability to codify ethics and
letting the perfect being be the enemy of the good,
begin with small steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He suggests we start with Kindergarten Ethics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;...However&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we prevent AI more advanced than us to develop because we're
afraid of being eradicated as a species by our creation ?
What if stalling AI cost us our future by removing a tool from our kit
that would allow us to deal with a threat that is beyond our native ability
to handle? Perhaps we should be advancing our technology exponentially, not slowing it.
This is a question that wasn't addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;...That said&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A book cannot be everything to all readers.
The potential importance of dissipation theory as a more fundamental
answer to the question "why is there life" than Darwinian theory
can provide, even though still controversial, made the book ultimately
worth the journey, and informed my stance on the topic of the threat
of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take-away of the intended message is that a
sufficiently ambitious goal executed efficiently
can and probably will lead to subgoals that
can and probably will cause problems for humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many systems that humankind created,
which seemed to take on a life of their own,
threatening to run away from us, some resulting in existential crisis.  Warcraft and ozone depletion are two examples.  So far, we’ve been able to recover in time and refactor these systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This means that to wisely decide what to do about AI development,
we humans need to confront not only traditional computational challenges,
but also some of the most obdurate questions in philosophy”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before reading this book I started out a skeptic of AI alarmism. 
I now take AI alarmism more seriously and
consider it to be more urgent than I did previously.
I previously thought that AI was indeed inevitable, but that
it was not inevitable for it to go rogue.  Moreover, even if
that were a possible outcome (which I felt it was), that we
had plenty of time to adapt it to us, and ourselves to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if life truly is driven by more fundamental laws
of nature that can override its core programming,
not only is this outcome more probable,
but it is inevitable unless we plan accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve tackled other wicked difficult problems,
such as the tragedy of the commons in its numerous forms, and myriad impossibility theorems.  These would seem to doom us all. And yet, here we are.
Thus far we have always discovered a workaround to impending doom, although it often
required a catastrophe to motivate us into serious action.
This is a problem that we can tackle. That said it isn't enough to take an optimistic view that human ingenuity has always
triumphed over nature, therefore, so it will again. 
The Ad Ignorantum fallacy is to argue that something is true because it has not been proven to be false. 
We need to have a deep fundamental understanding of life's
core drivers at a fundamental level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Before and after analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to reading this book I was in the middle ground between
the techno-optimists who believe that technology will solve all our problems,
and the techno-alarmists who believe our fate is sealed.
Does anyone here remember the alarm over
&lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2004-06-nanotechnology-grey-goo-myths.html"&gt;grey goo&lt;/a&gt;?
Just as the grey goo alarmists stirred healthy discussion that elevated awareness of the risks,
AI alarmism is healthy and necessary.  On the other hand,
I am one of those who looks at the "overnight success stories" of ML and AI and don't think
"wow that really snuck up on us", but rather
"it's about time".  We were supposed to have this stuff decades ago.
I thought, and still do think, that it will take decades more yet, and by then
we will have adapted the technology to ourselves, and ourselves to the technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, if we're not careful there is an important risk here. The risk is because we're dealing
with exponential processes. But as those of us who were early proponents of AI and ML
have seen, even exponential processes can take a long time to move from the
flat early stage to the hockey stick shaped curve that makes it seem like
it is all happening so suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we take a cue from our experience with the runaway replicators of grey goo -- where the solution
was to disallow unfettered replication. Simply disallow unfettered self-goal revision
in AIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet -- if life &lt;em&gt;will always&lt;/em&gt; find a way, then, as the author demonstrates in his
speculative fiction thought experiments, it is not enough to program
in defensive measures, failsafes, and circuit breakers.
We're not just dealing with AI here, we're potentially dealing with Artificial Life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;em&gt;Might I suggest a moratorium on Artificial Emotion til we resolve this?&lt;/em&gt; --&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/zkv-_LqTeQA/maxresdefault.jpg" width="500" height="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My key takeaway from this book:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding artificial intelligence is important.
Even more important is understanding artificial life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My two cents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That all said, halting progress is not the answer. I've seen this first-hand -- people throwing out a new tool (i.e., a new technology) because the tool was found to be flawed, only to be utterly pwned by their competition, who saw the same flaws in the tool but strived to find ways to workaround those flaws rather than throw out the new tool altogether. Lost opportunity is a risk that is often unaccounted for by people who are unaware of the economics underlying the ecosystem in which they reside. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The dirt on Hashgraph</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/the-dirt-on-hashgraph.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2018-01-07:/speech-to-text/the-dirt-on-hashgraph.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="emonocle byEMIIA" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-DpZwufJmu_Y/Wh6lGuTNRmI/AAAAAAAABUU/0W2PLj5w-j4ql9RE8Otwk5DrB3UcgKOGQCLcBGAs/s1600/hashgraph%2B%25282%2529.gif"&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;(emonocle byEMIIA)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;pssst!&lt;/em&gt; ... &lt;em&gt;have you heard about Hashgraph?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com"&gt;Hashgraph&lt;/a&gt; is a distributed ledger technology (DLT)
released by &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/"&gt;Swirlds&lt;/a&gt; (think: "Shared Worlds") in 2016.
It promises some of the most important benefits of blockchain without its biggest limitations.
It is comprised of a graph data structure which together with
the &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/downloads/SWIRLDS-TR-2016-01.pdf"&gt;Swirlds …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="emonocle byEMIIA" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-DpZwufJmu_Y/Wh6lGuTNRmI/AAAAAAAABUU/0W2PLj5w-j4ql9RE8Otwk5DrB3UcgKOGQCLcBGAs/s1600/hashgraph%2B%25282%2529.gif"&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;(emonocle byEMIIA)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;pssst!&lt;/em&gt; ... &lt;em&gt;have you heard about Hashgraph?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com"&gt;Hashgraph&lt;/a&gt; is a distributed ledger technology (DLT)
released by &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/"&gt;Swirlds&lt;/a&gt; (think: "Shared Worlds") in 2016.
It promises some of the most important benefits of blockchain without its biggest limitations.
It is comprised of a graph data structure which together with
the &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/downloads/SWIRLDS-TR-2016-01.pdf"&gt;Swirlds distributed consensus algorithm&lt;/a&gt;
provides &lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#what-is-bft"&gt;asynchronous byzantine fault tolerance&lt;/a&gt;, using what it calls "gossip about gossip."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whaaaat?&lt;/em&gt;  A system based on second hand rumors and some sort of whisper logs? We're really supposed to trust this thing?
Read on to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;About the author&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a developer of blockchain technologies, distributed ledger technologies,
and decentralized consensus systems.
At the time of writing this article I have no investment in any cryptocurrency, I do not work for or represent
any organization related to cryptocurrencies or distributed ledger technologies.
As of the time this article was posted, I am still learning about this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why am I writing this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hashgraph impressed on me the value of &lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#how-does-it-work"&gt;gossip&lt;/a&gt;.
Instead of waiting to share your opinion until you are absolutely certain of what you know, a
"gossip protocol" says to share your observations early and often.
So, here are mine about Hashgraph.
Hashgraph mathematically proves that
gossip can allow decentralized participants to rapidly share what they
have observed (as well as what they have heard second-hand from others),
and rapidly agree on what is to be believed. Who am I to argue with math?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How does Hashgraph use gossip?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are a member of a gossip network.
You tell some random participant what you know.  They tell you what they know.
Later, they tell some random participant what they know, which includes some
(possibly second hand) information they learned from you.
Eventually, participants are able to tally not only what they have observed,
but also what other participants are likely to have observed, based
on the gossip they've shared.  Given enough second-hand information
from enough credible witnesses, they can even predict the opinion of
participants with whom they have not communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timestamps are also calculated incorporating the consensus opinion of
when a event was observed, to counteract accidental or intentional timestamp errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we know from human nature, gossip spreads like wildfire.
Unlike how rumormills work in human society, when marshalled cleverly with the
proper algorithms, gossip turns out to be provably fair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How does Hashgraph compare to Bitcoin?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed consensus is an extremely useful concept in distributed computing.
For decades it was doable only among a small number of computers ("nodes").
Nakamoto's Bitcoin cryptocurrency  &lt;a href="http://vukolic.com/iNetSec_2015.pdf"&gt;presented a new way to achieve scalable decentralized consensus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Bitcoin demonstrating tremendous value, its blockchain plus Proof-of-Work (PoW) approach
presents several pitfalls. It is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wasteful since PoW expends huge amounts of computing power &lt;a href="http://www.nasdaq.com/article/byzantine-fault-tolerance-the-key-for-blockchains-cm810058"&gt;by design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slow, limited to tens of transactions per second.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject to allowing huge backlog of unconfirmed transactions to accumulate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network bandwidth intensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1311.0243"&gt;Susceptible to a 25% economic attack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bitcoin.org/en/full-node"&gt;Heavyweight&lt;/a&gt;. Full nodes must download the entire blockchain, currently 60 GB.  &lt;a href="https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Full_node"&gt;Lightweight nodes must trust the full nodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin protocol does not implement consensus
in the traditional distributed computing sense.
&lt;a href="http://vukolic.com/iNetSec_2015.pdf"&gt;Instead it achieves consensus via probabilistic agreement&lt;/a&gt;.
A primary goal of a cryptocurrency is to &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/TotallyOrderedSet.html"&gt;totally order&lt;/a&gt; transactions
on a &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/distributed-ledgers.asp"&gt;distributed ledger&lt;/a&gt;.
Cryptocurrencies avoid the need for a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cryptocurrency#Timestamping"&gt;trusted third party to timestamp transactions&lt;/a&gt;
added to the ledger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hashgraph also provides a total order on a distributed transaction ledger,
but does so using a &lt;a href="https://steemit.com/steemit/@decryptson/hashgraph"&gt;different approach&lt;/a&gt;.
Whereas the Bitcoin network builds up its transaction history in the form of a “blockchain”,
adding &lt;a href="https://bitcoinmagazine.com/articles/selfish-mining-a-25-attack-against-the-bitcoin-network-1383578440/"&gt;a new block on top of the previous block every ten minutes&lt;/a&gt;,
Hashgraph grows a time directed acyclic graph akin to a braided forest of trees
using "virtual voting" and &lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#how-does-it-work"&gt;"gossip about gossip"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Activity is divided into rounds.  At the beginning of a round,
each node communicates state with some random other node.
Since these two nodes already have a channel open, the random other node then shares back
state of its own that it knows first hand, perhaps along with some state that
it previously learned from another node.
After a new event has seen at least 2/3 of previous events, a round is concluded and a new round begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the new round is created, nodes say if they agree
upon the data contained in events of the preceding round.
The algorithm doesn't consider this to be voting per se, instead calling it a virtual election.
There is no leader to present a motion for vote, nor to tally votes.
Instead, to reach consensus on the events in the previous round,
nodes &lt;a href="https://medium.com/ibbc-io/hashgraph-for-dummies-90ddde3be9e2"&gt;verify that they are connected to these events&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(More strictly speaking,
it is actually about finding paths through the graph that connect events in the current round with past events in the previous round.
Please see : &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/downloads/SWIRLDS-TR-2016-02.pdf"&gt;How it Works (Graphically)&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, some applications could &lt;a href="http://ajitvadakayil.blogspot.com/2017/10/blockchain-smart-contracts-part-8-capt.html"&gt;dump all previous events&lt;/a&gt;.
In applications where the transaction timeseries can be
summarized by sufficient statistics, the hashgraph
history could be archived. This also means that &lt;em&gt;a new node doesn't need to load the entire hashgraph history&lt;/em&gt;,
greatly reducing the space required and allowing a &lt;a href="https://squawker.org/technology/blockchain-just-became-obsolete-the-future-is-hashgraph/"&gt;smartphone to act as a node&lt;/a&gt;.
There is no notion of full node and lightweight node, meaning that all nodes can participate in consensus and see the full ledger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Virtual elections: better than regular elections?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people consider Hashgraph to be more comparable to PBFT, Paxos, Raft, Zab,
and other consensus seeking systems that rely on leaders and
traditional voting schemes.
But Hashgraph eschews the comparison, because it doesn't use
traditional voting.
It comes to consensus about what happened, and when,
by cleverly tallying highly compressed event logs
based on "famous witnesses" that &lt;a href="https://www.swirlds.com/downloads/SWIRLDS-TR-2016-02.pdf"&gt;"strongly see"&lt;/a&gt; events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the timestamp of an event log is corrupted by a bad clock or is maliciously doctored,
this will usually have no effect on the consensus timestamp, because consensus opinion on
when something occurred is the median of timestamps observed by credible witnesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike some other directed acyclic graph algorithms, or even Paxos,
it really is quite easy to step through the Hashgraph algorithm.
I couldn't do it more succinctly here.
I'll again point the interested reader to whitepapers for how it works :
&lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/downloads/SWIRLDS-TR-2016-02.pdf"&gt;graphically&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/downloads/Swirlds-and-Sybil-Attacks.pdf"&gt;example voting scenarios&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hashgraph: the good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;a href="https://hackernoon.com/demystifying-hashgraph-benefits-and-challenges-d605e5c0cee5"&gt;fast&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#what-is-fairness"&gt;fair&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#preventing-sybil-attacks"&gt;secure&lt;/a&gt;.
It promises the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total ordering of events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong &lt;a href="http://the-paper-trail.org/blog/barbara-liskovs-turing-award-and-byzantine-fault-tolerance/"&gt;Byzantine Fault Tolerance&lt;/a&gt; (BFT),
the gold standard of industrial grade distributed consensus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimal network bandwidth, because it passes things only around once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provable 100% certainty on the order of transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it is fast and requires low network bandwidth, it can be used as a distributed memory system.
Because it provides a total order on transactions, it can be used as a multi-master database.
Because it does not use Proof-of-Work, it does not require unnecessary computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paypal and Visa tend to be held up as benchmarks or
at the very least as future milestones for a DLT to achieve in order to
replace an existing mainstream currency, payment system, or other commercial transaction logging systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the transactions per second (tps) of PoW versus Paypal and Visa :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PoW Blockchain (Etherium, Bitcoin) : &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt; 10 tps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paypal : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.altcointoday.com/bitcoin-ethereum-vs-visa-paypal-transactions-per-second/"&gt;200 tps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visa : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://mybroadband.co.za/news/security/190348-visanet-handling-100000-transactions-per-minute.html"&gt;2K tps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://lightning.network/lightning-network-paper.pdf"&gt;50K x/sec&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of these, only PoW is a BFT DLT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, because of its positioning and licensing, Hashgraph is more directly comparable to Hyperledger, which is
another scalable DLT using a Practical Byzantine Fault Tolerance (PBFT) consensus algorithm.
Other comparable enterprise-grade transaction processing systems include
LMAX and its variants, such as &lt;a href="http://lmax-exchange.github.io/disruptor/"&gt;LMAX Disruptor&lt;/a&gt;
and Bitshares. LMAX is not a DLT, and Bitshares is billed as a decentralized exchange.
That said, if we are going to use Visa and Paypal for comparison, then we might as well
include these for context. Their ts/sec are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.hyperledger.org/about"&gt;Hyperledger&lt;/a&gt; : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.altoros.com/blog/hyperledgers-sawtooth-lake-aims-at-a-thousand-transactions-per-second/"&gt;1K tps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/chain-cloud-company-blog/hyperledger-vs-corda-pt-1-3723c4fa5028"&gt;10K tps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bitshares : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://bitshares.org/technology/industrial-performance-and-scalability/"&gt;100K tps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LMAX : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://qconsf.com/sf2010/sf2010/presentation/LMAX+-+How+to+do+over+100K+concurrent+transactions+per+second+at+less+than+1ms+latency.html"&gt;100K tps (2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/lmax.html"&gt;6M tps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hashgraph's inventor says it will be able to attain &lt;a href="https://www.hiddenforcespod.com/leemon-baird-hashgraph-distributed-ledger-technology-blockchain/"&gt;250K+ tps&lt;/a&gt;,
more with sharding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the catch?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hashgraph is currently being deployed in &lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#is-there-a-cryptocurrency"&gt;private, permissioned-based networks&lt;/a&gt;,
although its designers propose means for implementing &lt;a href="http://www.swirlds.com/downloads/Swirlds-and-Sybil-Attacks.pdf"&gt;nonpermissioned and hybrid networks&lt;/a&gt;.
How well it can be adapted to a truly decentralised public ledger remains to be seen, because it assumes that a node can determine :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addresses of random nodes in the network for messaging, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of other nodes N in the network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because the algorithm requires a node to be able to (a) pick another node at random, and (b) know the value of ⅔ * N.
It needs a means of registering and unregistering of members in the network,
whereas public blockchains allow nodes to sign in and out to the network without any notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following seem to be the major showstoppers for many members of the cryptocurrency development community:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hashgraph.com/faq/#is-there-a-cryptocurrency"&gt;There is no Hashgraph public ledger or cryptocurrency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US Patents #&lt;a href="http://www.leemon.com/papers/2017b.pdf"&gt;9,646,029&lt;/a&gt;, #&lt;a href="http://www.leemon.com/papers/2016b4.pdf"&gt;9,529,923&lt;/a&gt;, #&lt;a href="http://www.leemon.com/papers/2016b3.pdf"&gt;9,390,154&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Requires a license to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A passing thought&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://tech.mit.edu/V123/N8/8voting.8n.html"&gt;Arrow's Theorem&lt;/a&gt; proves that no voting system is fair.
I'm no &lt;a href="https://www.princeton.edu/~cuff/voting/theory.html"&gt;voting theorist&lt;/a&gt;,
but in my (extremely humble) opinion, Hashgraph comes pretty close.
It makes one want to believe in democracy again. Real-time continuous nationwide elections anyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for helpful edits to &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@twittner"&gt;Josh Quittner&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/thewillhuang"&gt;Will Huang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gregorykennedy/"&gt;Gregory Kennedy&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://blog.valkyrierobotics.com/"&gt;Marcus Plutowski&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concluding remark&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://scontent.cdninstagram.com/t51.2885-15/s320x320/e35/25009793_144878492834781_2739446234354810880_n.jpg"&gt;DYOR&lt;/a&gt; !
Consider this to be informed gossip. But do share your gossip with me too. The math says to, so, yeah just do what the math says.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>on Bleu scores and transcription rates</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/on-bleu-scores-and-transcription-rates.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2017-04-30:/speech-to-text/on-bleu-scores-and-transcription-rates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Work in progress]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Reference audio vs noisy recordings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, each service performs better on audio recorded in a
quiet setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM and Google performed about the same over high quality
audio recorded in a quiet setting using a medium quality
microphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM was better able to generate transcripts for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Work in progress]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Reference audio vs noisy recordings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, each service performs better on audio recorded in a
quiet setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM and Google performed about the same over high quality
audio recorded in a quiet setting using a medium quality
microphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM was better able to generate transcripts for
my lower quality recordings obtained in noisy settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be due to a custom (which they refer to as a "narrowband")
setting that IBM
provides that is specifically provided to accommodate
low-bitrate recordings. That setting also tends to generate longer
transcripts for higher bitrate recordings that are especially noisy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may also have to do with the encoding used. I needed to transcode
every audio file to the encoding required by Google's service, and it
is possible that this transcoding step could be tuned to give better accuracy.
I haven't attempted any rigorous tuning of either service at this stage of
my experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a work in progress.  I am hoping to do a direct file-by-file
comparison of the two services once I am confident that I am
configuring my settings to use Google's api to the best of its capability.
However I have obtained some cursory comparisons on the current results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Processing seconds per minute : about the same&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM and Google process the audio in about the same amount of time.
Google is somewhat faster at the actual transcription processing.
However, Google requires that the file be
uploaded to Google Storage first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;IBM Transcribed/Processed : 7281/8415&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM was able to transcribe 87% of the files submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Google Transcribed/Processed : 3521/8415&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transcription rate (42%) was lower for two main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was a file size limit.
Files larger than ~80MB require a prior arrangement,
whereas IBM was able to process files of all sizes submitted to the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second main reason is that IBM has a custom setting for
low-bit rate recordings. Google failed to generate a transcript
for many files that were below the file size limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Transcript words per minute of audio (IBM/Google) : 102.0/9.8&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google's api doesn't have a setting for handling low-bitrate
recordings similar to IBM's narrowband setting.
The number of transcript
words generated per minute of audio was much lower for Google
even after adjusting for transcription rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Comparison on reference documents&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following comparisons were made over 245 reference documents.
The reference transcripts were transcribed using a speech-to-text
transcription software that was trained to my voice,
in a quiet environment, using a hand-held medium quality wired microphone.
Most of the errors were manually corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google generated a transcript for 210 out of the 245 reference documents (86%),
and IBM generated a transcript for 243 of the 245 (99%).
The Bleu scores over these reference documents are fairly comparable,
with IBM performing slightly better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bleu score deciles" src="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/blob/master/images/bleu_score_deciles.png?raw=true"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When measured using Ratcliff-Obershelp similarity,
Google fares slightly better across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ratcliff score deciles" src="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/blob/master/images/ratcliff_score_deciles.png?raw=true"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Comparison over all audio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section analyzes the number of transcripts
that are generated, and the number of words per transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comparison was over 8,415 audio files that were submitted to each
service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marked differences between IBM Watson and Google transcription arise
when comparing transcription rates and number of words generated when run
on audio collected out in the wild. Of 8,415 such audio, IBM generated
transcripts for 7,227, while Google was able
to generate a transcript for 3,521.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Total Word Counts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of 8,415 audio files attempted, Google generated 3,521 transcripts.
Those 3,521 transcripts contain total of 485,334 words,
an average of 137 words per transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IBM Watson generated 7,227 transcripts, extracting
9,511,743 words out of those transcripts.
This gives an average of 1,316 words per transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Word Count Deciles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these transcripts that Google failed to generate were simply due
to the file size exceeding quota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However Google also failed to generate any transcript words
for many other files that did not exceed the file size quota.
It also generated a much lower word count per transcript for
audio that was from a noisy or low bit rate recording.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to illustrate this is by examining the word count deciles over the
transcripts that were successfully generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following table gives the word counts deciles over the
transcripts generated by each service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;API&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;min&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;9&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;max&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Google&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;459&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4892&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IBM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;278&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;501&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;916&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1137&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1409&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1722&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2080&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2450&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8490&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Word count deciles" src="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/blob/master/images/word_count_deciles.png?raw=true"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>on batch processing audio speech to text</title><link href="https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/on-batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2017-04-22:/speech-to-text/on-batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How not to wreck a nice beach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Quora" src="https://qph.ec.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-609e5b0b3c91845ab81f0d4448df864f-c"&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Quora)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People nowadays commonly use speech-to-text tools for myriad uses,
including writing text messages, entering todo lists,
and writing emails.  However, increasing numbers of enterprising
sorts including just plain folk are starting to warm up to
using dictation software for writing longer form …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How not to wreck a nice beach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Quora" src="https://qph.ec.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-609e5b0b3c91845ab81f0d4448df864f-c"&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Quora)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People nowadays commonly use speech-to-text tools for myriad uses,
including writing text messages, entering todo lists,
and writing emails.  However, increasing numbers of enterprising
sorts including just plain folk are starting to warm up to
using dictation software for writing longer form content
such as journals and even novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dictation software has been generally available for many years,
in the form of
commercial off the shelf application software, text editors in desktop
operating systems, notepads in tablet devices,
email clients in mobile phones,
and more recently in cloud-based document editors, available
to the user from any device that can run a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if you have a large-ish number of audio files?
It turns out there isn't a comparably inexpensive and easy way
to handle even modestly sized
batches of files using those just aforementioned tools.
There do exist commercially available alternatives, which will gladly
take those batches of audio files off your hands and return
high quality text. But these are still rather
human labor intensive, which means that they remain expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical going rate is about a $1/minute, although with a bit
of coding effort (typically meaning slicing files into uniform size work units,
farming said work units out to a distributed online on-demand work force
such as mechanical turk, then resplicing the files back together)
apparently can bring the price down to somewhat, say 70 cents/minute.
(The slicing and resplicing is needed for quality assurance as well
as to reduce privacy and security issues.)
That 70 cents a minute is still rather unaffordable to the typical consumer who is a tad long-winded,
much less the odd sort who just happens to have a boat load of such files.
Not to mention the concerns related to having unknown on-demand workers
hearing an early preview of your memoirs
(cf. &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/04/long-form-voice-transcription/"&gt;Long Form Voice Transcription, Wired, April 2016&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, an affordable alternative is emerging, that is,
if you're willing to write a bit of code.
All of the hyperscale cloud api providers have made their deep
learning speech-to-text models available for a small fraction of the
dollar cost of the aforementioned human-corrected transcription services,
and two of them are now appealing enough for use by individuals
or nonprofits to apply to long form content.
Currently you can get cloud api based speech transcription
for
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Cloud-API-Pricing"&gt;prices ranging from 2 to 2.4 cents per minute&lt;/a&gt;,
with an additional allowance free on a monthly basis.
Moreover, they effortlessly handle large batches in a single bound.
You upload your files to the cloud, offloading the
processing from your laptop. Whereas your desktop software or even
embedded operating system software would slow your entire machine down
to a crawl during this process
you could be processing batches of files in parallel
up in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there is still that small issue of having to write some code
in order to get this amazing cost and time reduction.
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text"&gt;I went and wrote said code.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this amazing capability is generally available
at a reasonable price
to anyone with a laptop, internet connection,
and credit card with an embarrassingly low limit.
But it isn't all peaches and chocolate just yet.
There is a still a ways to go before these APIs are reliably useful
for converting conversational audio recorded in the wild using
mobile phones amidst the usual ambient sounds.
Nonetheless, the results are tantalizingly good enough
and the pricing dramatically low enough that the time has come to dip
my metaphorical toes in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to write more about my experiences using these
powerful cloud APIs, so stay tuned if this is of interest
to you.  Although I myself tend to cringe when the blogger ends
their post by promising an enticing followup, which invariably never
comes.  But I really do sincerely intend to write more on this.
Of course, that's what they would all say, I'm sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already compiled a backlog of interesting results just waiting
to be converted into
intriguing visuals and wrapped in witty yet insightful prose. Promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually you don't need to wait until then, as
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Background"&gt;here is some additional background on the project&lt;/a&gt;.
Here are the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Findings"&gt;results of a preliminary comparison between IBM and Google&lt;/a&gt;.
Here are
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Comparison-over-reference-documents"&gt;results made over reference documents&lt;/a&gt;.
And here are some
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Comparison-of-transcript-word-count"&gt;results made over audio collected in the wild&lt;/a&gt;.
There are several conclusions that can be drawn from these findings,
which will be the subject of a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing, my findings indicate to me that I should be able to
extract useful text from my recordings,
albeit probably not for the purpose of transcribing meeting minutes.
The transcript text generated by the cloud API is largely recognizable to me, although
that is often in the same way as my handwriting is recognizable to me
because I vaguely remember generating it.
The error rates are still too high
for these transcripts to allow me to reliably parse meaningful
whole sentences much less serve as document of record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These cloud APIs do not have the same quality as
do personalized devices. Voicemail transcripts provided by my
phone are subjectively better than what I'm seeing with these cloud APIs.
One reason is that because the cloud APIs cannot be
trained on my voice, although IBM does allow specifying
a &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/watson/developercloud/doc/speech-to-text/custom.html#addWords"&gt;custom language model&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accuracy being provided
by the cloud APIs may be suitable for
indexing audio files to make them more easily searchable
(although phonemes might turn out to be the better data unit
for indexing audio than words,
&lt;a href="https://twimlai.com/from-particle-physics-to-audio-ai-with-scott-stephenson/"&gt;e.g., Deepgram&lt;/a&gt;).
I fully expect the current results to
be adequately informative to support meaningful textmining and trend
analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon reviewing the current batch of results it is fascinating
to me how a badly transcribed
sequence of just a few words in a row can turn large swaths of text
into complete gibberish. If you tell a linguist you intend to
&lt;em&gt;recognize speech&lt;/em&gt; they might bid you luck, but an evesdropping
surfer taking that to mean instead
that you intend to &lt;em&gt;wreck a nice beach&lt;/em&gt; might wish you harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We humans are pretty amazing in our ability
to understand each other's muffled speech despite the
poor connection and background noise
much less the tinnitus and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, I foresee a not too distant future where
it will be possible to cheaply attain human level accuracy
transcription of speaker-independent long-form speech
from noisy recordings obtained using mobile devices. Culminating in,
as &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/04/long-form-voice-transcription/"&gt;Wired's Jesse Jarnow&lt;/a&gt; puts it,
'bizarre kinds of unforeseen societal change'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then, court stenographers shouldn't have much to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="disqus_thread"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;

var disqus_config = function () {
this.page.url = "https://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/"
this.page.identifier = "pluteski-github-io-speech-to-text"
};
(function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
s.src = 'https://pluteski-github-io-speech-to-text.disqus.com/embed.js';
s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
(d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
})();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript"&gt;comments.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;fin&lt;/h6&gt;</content></entry></feed>