<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Plutosoft Delimited - misc</title><link href="http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/</id><updated>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Batch processing audio speech to text.</title><link href="http://pluteski.github.io/speech-to-text/batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Plutowski</name></author><id>tag:pluteski.github.io,2017-04-22:/speech-to-text/batch-processing-audio-speech-to-text.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Recognize speech, not wreck a nice beach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are starting to warm up to speech-to-text tools available from
commercial off the shelf application software, text editors in desktop,
notepads and email clients in mobile operating systems,
and cloud-based document editors.
But what if you have a large-ish number of audio …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Recognize speech, not wreck a nice beach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are starting to warm up to speech-to-text tools available from
commercial off the shelf application software, text editors in desktop,
notepads and email clients in mobile operating systems,
and cloud-based document editors.
But what if you have a large-ish number of audio files?
It turns out there isn't an easy way to handle this using those tools,
and the commercially available alternatives are human labor intensive,
and therefore, rather unaffordable to the typical consumer who just
happens to have a boat load of such files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, an affordable alternative is emerging, if
you're willing to write a bit of code.
The hyperscale cloud api providers are making their deep
learning models available for a small fraction of the dollar cost,
and able to handle large batches in a single bound,
although there is that small issue of having to write some code
in order to get this amazing cost and time reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although generally available,
there is a ways to go before these APIs are generally useful
for converting noisy audio recorded in the wild using
mobile phones.  Nonetheless, the results are good enough
and the pricing low enough that it may time to dip your metaphorical
toes in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is some &lt;a href="https://github.com/pluteski/speech-to-text/wiki/Background"&gt;background&lt;/a&gt;
on the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cozy little minimalist theme used for this is site is brought to
you by &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>